<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A ritch storehouse or treasurie for nobilitye and gentlemen, which in Latine is called Nobilitas literata, written by a famous and excellent man, Iohn Sturmius, and translated into English by T.B. Gent. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed</title>
            <title>Nobilitas literata. English</title>
            <author>Sturm, Johannes, 1507-1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117934</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853143</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853143</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18511</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13115)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18511)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 357:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A ritch storehouse or treasurie for nobilitye and gentlemen, which in Latine is called Nobilitas literata, written by a famous and excellent man, Iohn Sturmius, and translated into English by T.B. Gent. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed</title>
                  <title>Nobilitas literata. English</title>
                  <author>Sturm, Johannes, 1507-1589.</author>
                  <author>Browne, Thomas, of Lincoln's Inn.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40, 33-48 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Denham, dwelling in pater noster row at the signe of the Starre.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1570.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Nobilitas literata.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Thomas Browne.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18511:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18511:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A ritch Storehouſe</hi> or Treaſurie for <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitye and Gentlemen,</hi> which in Latine is called <hi>Nobilitas literata, written by a</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and excellent man, Iohn Sturmius, and tranſlated into Engliſh by T.B. Gent.</p>
            <p>Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> by Henrie Denham, dwelling in pater noſter row at the ſigne of the Starre.</p>
            <p>Anno Domini. 1570.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18511:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18511:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, <hi>vertuous, and my ſinguler good</hi> Lord, Lord Philip Hovvard Erle of Surrey, all felicitie and happyneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> HAVE RIGHT vertuous and ryght Honorable Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing led by the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler zeale &amp; great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, which I knowe you haue to obtayne vnto learning, &amp; ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly moued by my ſeruice and duetie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning vnto your Lordſhip, aduentured the tranſlation of thys ſmall volume, more excellent and precious, than long or tedious: wherein I truſt, if you vouchſafe but to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy ſmall traueyle, that you ſhall reape infinite and exceeding great commoditie: neyther doe I deſire you to beſtowe part of the day in the reading and ſtudie hereof, bicauſe I haue tranſlated and dedicated the ſame vnto your Lordſhip: But rather for the golden and Honorable precepts therein contayned: and for the Noble and highe eſtate of them, for whome it was firſt of all compoſed. But peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture my euill and vnskilfull handeling hereof, may
<pb facs="tcp:18511:3"/>after you haue begonne to reade it, in ſhort tyme and before you reache the ende, wearye your minde, and hinder your good and prayſewoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy diſire: which, as I feare, may vnhappily come to paſſe, ſo I truſt your Lordſhip will warylie preuent the ſame by adioyning the Latine therevnto: that euer as you are diſcouraged by my rude and vnfyled phraſe to go forwardes, you maye by the other, which is precious and goodly, be made loth to giue ouer till you come to the concluſion thereof: which if your Lordſhip vouchſafe to doe, I ſhall thinke my payne and traueyle, to be but pleaſure and paſtyme, and receyue a good and ample recompence for the ſame, and you reape ſuch fruite and commoditie as I wyſhed you ſhould: and thus vnwylling to be tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or troubleſome vnto you, I ende, wiſhing all ioy felicitie and happyneſſe vnto your good Lordſhip, that may be wiſhed to any, as the loue and fauour of God and the Prince, long lyfe, proſperous ſucceſſe in your affayres, and after the chaunge of this lyfe, the greateſt happineſſe of all, lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your Lordſhips to commaunde, Thomas Browne, from Lyncolnes Inne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18511:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the friendly <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Earned and moſt friendlye Reader: if Bookes gaine credite or diſcredite by their tranſlators, I maye iuſtly feare that this worthy worke by my euill handling ſhall be diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and be but of ſmall account with thee. But ſyth that works be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted good, neyther are they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned as bad for their tranſlators or reporters, but be praiſed for their excellencie &amp; goodneſſe, or condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for their baſeneſſe and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I mooue not thee to lyke thys treatiſe, bicauſe I interpreted it, but I beſeeche thee to allowe it for the goodneſſe and excellent matter, plentifully flowing therein. But our time (alas) is ſo inclined, and as it
<pb facs="tcp:18511:4"/>were naturally bent to beſtow vpon barren and vnhoneſt fruites, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and golden names, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can vertuous and prayſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy workes enioye their due and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued tytles, being foreſtauled and defrauded by the euill, neyther good deedes poſſeſſe their owne, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy termes being preuented by the meane. And now men rather labor to declare howe muche they can: then, what and howe much they ought to ſaye: yeelding themſelues ſooner ſubiectes and bondſlaues to their lawleſſe luſtes, than truly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhinge their vpryght iudgements, and to vtter rather in vnſeaſonable time painted wordes and ſmooth Rhetoricke, than matter good and precious, ſo that neyther the condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the cauſe, whether it be good or badde, can moue them to ſaye ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or leſſe. For if the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie
<pb facs="tcp:18511:4"/>of this ſmall Treatiſe, eyther for the golden preceptes herein, the lyke whereof hath neuer earſt bene taught by any, eyther for the profite hereby to thee (gentle Reader) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing ſhoulde with deſerued com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation bee rewarded: I of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie muſt eyther coyne newe wordes, the auncient already being employed on lewde and peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wicked matters, or wiſhe that the vulgar ſpeache of commending might bee kept vntill ſome worthye matters were inuented, whereon wel and happily to beſtow it. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauing no plentie of goodlye wordes, I am enforced to keepe my iudgement to my ſelfe, beſeeching thee to giue vnto the worthyneſſe of the matter due and deſerued ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. Thus doing, thou ſhalt not only encourage me hereafter to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the tranſlating of ſome lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:18511:5"/>matter, but in the meane time giue me iuſt cauſe to thinke my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyle herein to bee verie well em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed: wiſhing that it may yeelde thee, ſemblable profite, that wilte vouchſafe to reade it, as it did plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to mee, that tooke the paynes to tranſlate it: and thus as thy friend I bid thee fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, and wiſh thee happily to doe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By T.B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18511:5"/>
            <head>¶A ritch Storehouſe or <hi>Treaſure for nobilitie</hi> and Gentlemen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong (O Phillip) haue you intreated me, and nowe your Broother Anthony doth ioyne with you in the ſame requeſt: that I would ſhewe you ſome waye, order, and trade of ſtudie: in the which, men of learning haue in my iudgement béene exerciſed: and therewith may be alſo fit and apt for your yeres, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and nobilitie. Wherein I would gladly yéelde my ſelfe to ſatiſfie your willes: if I might be able to conteyne in one ſmall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume to ſo large theames. Whereof, the one would require a long and copious diſcourſe, to declare what I take to haue bene the vſe and cuſtome of the learned, and chiefely of the Gréekes and Latines. But in the other I will indeuor to further you in thys your prayſe worthy and earneſt traueile in ſtudy: and from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one I will chooſe out to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: euen ſomuch as the matter it ſelfe ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:18511:6"/>ſéeme to require: meaning to intreate more largely of the other at another time, when I ſhall haue leyſure, and when it ſhall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for your ſtudies. But truely at thys preſent we are to conſider of you and your brother: betwéene whome there is ſmall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of yeares, as alſo a great agréement and ſimilitude in diſpoſition and wytte. For in you both there appeareth one will: equall knowledge, and one ſelfe ſame contention: to the which, you are now moued, as well by your owne inclination and zeale to good lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: as long ſince you were by the inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor and example of your teacher <hi>George Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricius,</hi> after whome ſuccéeded <hi>Wolfangus</hi> his brother: who ſo lyued two yeares wyth you, that he thereby hath reaped trebble fruite: ye and that right honeſt. For he was greatly delighted with hys brothers moſte pleaſaunt companye: and taught you by his example and recogniſed his woonted ſtudies of learning, and hath ſo obtayned thoſe thrée commodities (as you know) that it ſéemed he abſented himſelfe, from <hi>Beichelingo,</hi> and from his friends, not ſo much for himſelfe as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18511:6"/>for your cauſe: and for the ſame reaſon is now reſident at <hi>Lutecia:</hi> not onely to gyue you enſample, but alſo ſéeming to haue gone thither before purpoſely for your ſake.</p>
            <p>But that I may returne from whence I ſomething haue digreſſed: I wyll appoynt and preſcribe you a ſpeciall time when to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and alſo what your ſtudie and exerciſe ſhall be: wherein all my conſultation ſhall conſiſt, and in the ſame I will haue conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration both of your yeres, capacitie of witte, and ſuch your vnderſtanding in learning as you haue gotten alreadie: I will foreſhewe what order you ſhall aquaynt your ſelues withall, theſe thrée yeares next enſuing, and what to take vppon you, that when the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendes of Ianuarie by courſe hath returned thrice, whereſoeuer you ſhall become, your talke may be diſcréete, good, Latine, eligant, and plentyfull. Which in myne opinion is one of the endes whereat you ſhoote: I meane a learned lyfe, wherein you haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded my aduiſe. The other ende pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to vertue, which requireth to be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at an other time. And ſurely if you ioyne
<pb facs="tcp:18511:7"/>to the Nobleneſſe of your houſe, and to your ryches and other commodities, vertue and learning (euen as you earſt haue begonne to doe, and as all Gentlemen ought to doe) what thing is there apperteyning to felicitie and a happie lyfe but you haue it alreadie, if it be in your power ſo long as thoſe things which God hath giuen you are not taken from you, neyther by fatall miſhap, nor by force, nor fraude, and yet vertue, and godlyneſſe, and the knowledge and vnderſtanding of great matters, doth helpe much both to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of theſe things while you haue them, and to the comfort of your minde, if you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to loſe them: ſo that you can not be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the chiefeſt ſtep and degrée of feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie: but ſhall alwayes haue a place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to abyde. And truely although it be not my purpoſe to diſcourſe of vertue, wherein reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion muſt haue the chiefeſt honor and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigntie: yet leaſt vertue ſhould be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of other men as a thing vnneſſarie for the learned, or leaſt men may déeme mée ſo to make account: therefore in this our begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning we haue made mention thereof: prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18511:7"/>bicauſe in this part, and in this our purpoſe we haue néede of thrée vertues aboue the reſt, without the which neyther our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor your deſire can take anye great effect. Firſt, therfore diligence is very requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, without the which, euen goodly wyttes and ſinguler capacities doe not attaine vnto much: Secondly, temperaunce and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt meaſure in delightes, which is the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den or kéeper of diligence, and the preſeruer both of the wyt and ſoundneſſe of nature: Thirdlye, conſtancie in them both: that thoſe things whatſoeuer are begonne, may be perfited and brought to effect. The which vertues ſhall then be thought to be in vs in déede, when neyther our diligence ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our ſtrength: nor temperaunce ſhall hinder our helth: nor conſtancy ſhal bréede in vs to great an obſtinacie: not that vertues are vices, but for that, that vices doe deceyue vs oftentimes with the ſimilitude and ymage of vertue, wée will that vertue be chéerefull, ſounde, and wylling to followe: and it beſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a ſtudent to be of behauiour amiable, of body helthfull, of minde tractable, not loly
<pb facs="tcp:18511:8"/>wanton, nor womanly delicate, nor froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſtubborne.</p>
            <p>Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt two vertues which I haue recounted and may not be ſecluded from this our diſcourſe, ought to be agréeable to the ſtrength of the bodye, and as for conſtancie and ſtedfaſtneſſe they doe not onely reſpect the ende of our ſtudie and lyfe: but alſo they are to be vſed in all &amp; ſinguler actions, which are diſcretely begoonne. Now therefore ſith there appeareth excellent ſignes and tokens of theſe vertues in you: the which in theſe yeres I haue often perceyued, I doe willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accept you: and as I ſhall be able, I wyll ayde you in this your great indeuor and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie honeſt traueyle well knowne to me.</p>
            <p>But I am firſt to conſider: how farre you haue waded in the ſtudie of letters: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may not onely auoyde the eſcaping of any thing: but alſo to prouide that I do not ſeme to giue you councell in ſome pointes, when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is atchieued, and paſt alreadie. You haue learned therefore as I am enformed by your brother <hi>Wolfango:</hi> &amp; as I perceyue by your letters all thoſe precepts and rules of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18511:8"/>tongue, ſpecially which are neceſſary for the vnderſtanding of wryters. And in the ſame tongue you haue gotten ſuch ſtore and choyſe both of wordes, and phraſes (which are the Images of things and of ſentences) that therewithall you are ſufficiently furniſhed to the vſe of wryting, and practiſe of your Penne, ſo that ſome ſkil in Logick and Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick be not wanting thereto, by the which two Artes, the ſtyle hath bene alwayes direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and gouerned: And ſurely, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ſtill thoſe things, as I truſt you do: which you firſt hearde of mée in Rhetorick and Logick: and the which afterwarde you recogniſed with your teacher <hi>Seueno:</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire nothing elſe, but diligent annotation in reading: and in writing painefulneſſe. Now in the Gréeke thus farre you haue procéeded, that in the preceptes of the tongue there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth no labour, I meane eyther for the ſingle worde, or for the phraſe. To the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyting wherof, the labor in vnderſtanding is not ſo painefull, as the obſeruation ſhall bée delectable and pleaſant in comparing and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying of the ſame. Yet I am not ignorant
<pb facs="tcp:18511:9"/>that ſomething is vnknowne vnto you in theſe preceptes which you vnderſtande not: neuertheleſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowledge which you haue, is ſufficient for my purpoſe, and for the thing you requyre of mée. For although <hi>Homers Vlyſſes</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſaye a man of great experience and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, had ſéene dyuers coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and knew the diſpoſitions of a number of men as <hi>Homer</hi> wryteth, yet it is credible that in euery countrie and Citie, ſome there were whom he deſired not to know: neyther would he vnderſtand what was done in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie familie: But onely learne thoſe things, which ſhould leade him to that, which he had deuiſed and purpoſed in his minde before. Nay rather he neuer erred nor offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded more: than when he was ouerlong holden with the loue of <hi>Calypſo:</hi> And ſuffered his indeuor and actiue courage with noble prayſe, to be buried in the darkeneſſe of the dungion. As therefore it is likely that this man, whome <hi>Homer</hi> doth make moſt wiſe, did traueyle through ſundrie countries: ſo alſo we muſt traueile in theſe Artes, whereof we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18511:9"/>ſpoken, neither ought we to make lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſtay in the particuler precepts, than ſhall be ſufficient to vnderſtande the wordes and phraſes thereof. And as he in all his aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and traueyles, had his minde fixed on ſtonie <hi>Ithaca</hi> his natiue Countrie, haſting thyther by all meanes he coulde: in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner muſt wée goe forwarde, towarde the ende of our ſtudies and ſcope of our lyfe: the which for the moſt part by nature is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced aloft, and is harde to atchieue. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we haue to ſpeake hereafter, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider which way we may atteyne and come vnto it, neyther am I in doubt: but that in this aboundance and plentie of welth, your intent is to attaine to honeſtie and learning: of the which two, one belongeth to the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of nurture: the other pertaynes to our preſent purpoſe: and bringeth great help vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the former: and truely in this world, that lyfe is bleſſed in mine opinion: which to the antiquitie of parentage, ioyneth godly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and good behauiour: and doth garniſhe and bewtifie aboundant welth with excellent learning. Therefore will I deuyde thys my
<pb facs="tcp:18511:10"/>treatiſe of precepts into two partes: whereof the one concerneth the knowledge of things which poliſheth the minde: the other pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the exerciſe of the tongue and practiſe of ſpéeche, which is to be vttred diſcretely and eligantly, and being repreſented to the eares of the hearers, it doth ſhewe a ſwéete and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred conſent of the minde: which we may more eaſily vnderſtande than that muſicall harmonie of the heauenly Spheres, which we neuer heard, though <hi>Pythagoras</hi> taught it long ago. But to begin with the firſt part, that is to ſay, with the knowledge of things: I ſée not what may more become you, or better ſet forth your nobilitie, than the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of ciuill pollicie, which the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians terme <hi>Politicen.</hi> Which if you obtaine as you ought to doe: you ſhall greatly beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie both your countrie, and alſo your houſe and kindred. For what is better or what more excellent: than for a noble man to be learned &amp; politike: which two, doe contayne all learning, vertue, and Religion: wherfore whether it be an Arte or ſcience, or elſe a vertue and fealtie, wée will declare by what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18511:10"/>way you may attaine to the knowledge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that you may not onely liue profitable to others, but alſo pleaſantly to your ſelues: and that you may appeare to haue bene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and welcome among your friends, at home pleaſant and gentle, and abroade ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable: nowe this knowledge of ciuill poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, may well be learned in thoſe bookes which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath written of a common welth. But bicauſe the foundations of noble Cities conſiſt in the vertuous manners of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens: morall ſcience maye well be ioyned with ciuill policie: which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo handled in manye bookes, but of all the knowledge of ſtories doth ſpeciallye helpe. Wherein we may ſée the diuers and variable beginnings of common welthes, and howe the ſame haue bene preſerued, and how they haue bene altered and ouerthrowne, beſides ſtore of good councell in doubtfull and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine matters: &amp; ſundrie examples to frame our lyfe by, verilye I know not wherein you ſhould better beſtowe your traueyle, than in this ſtudie: ſpecially after that you are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently furniſhed with the precepts of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<pb facs="tcp:18511:11"/>Logick, and Rhetorick. In obteyning whereof, you muſt haue a regard of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine ſpéech: that it be not corrupted with the varietie of tongues, and diuerſitie of words: which are proper, and peculier to euery Arte and language, and to euery wryter and in euery kinde: for oft times in the handling of one matter, dyuers Authors doe greatly differ one from another, both in placing their wordes, and in the whole order of framing their ſentences: for <hi>Herodotus</hi> is a Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and in the ſame countrie and language, I meane the Gréeke. <hi>Thucidodes,</hi> is alſo a Hiſtoriographer: and the ſtyle of them both is goodly and bewtifull, yet how greatly doe they differ in ſwéeteneſſe, in grauitie, in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of woordes, in figures of Sentences, and as it were, in a certaine tranſforming of partes, members, and periodes: and finally, of the whole order of compoſition: The actes of the Romaynes were wrytten by <hi>Caeſar, Liuius,</hi> and <hi>Tacitus.</hi> But what diuerſitie is there betwixt them in all theſe ornamentes which I now rehearſed: But yet doth <hi>Tully</hi> more differ from them all: and euen <hi>Ciceros</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18511:11"/>owne bookes, haue in them verie great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie. Write you an Epiſtle in that kinde of ſtyle, in the which <hi>Tully</hi> wrote the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aeme</hi> of his Dration, that he made in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Milo,</hi> although you ſhall finde ſome amonge the vnſkilfull that will commende your doing: yet thoſe that be of right iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will diſalowe it, and thinke you haue paſſed the rules and boundes of that which is méete and ſéemely. Wherefore, we muſt take héede that as knowledge of thinges doe ſtore vs with ſubſtaunce to the handeling of dyuers matters: ſo it doe not hurt our ſtyle with ſtraunge wordes and phraſes. Not as though eyther theſe were no Latines, or the other no Grecians: but for this reaſon that as horſemen and footemen went not a lyke: nor the Romaynes, nor Grecians did not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes weare one kinde of garment, both in the Senate, in the Court, and in their houſes at home. So in the handelyng and wryting vpon dyuers thinges, they followe not one manner of ſtyle: nor vſed not alwayes one forme of ſpéech. I commende ſome man for ſéeing of Rome: and I lyke well that you
<pb facs="tcp:18511:12"/>haue heard <hi>Cratippus</hi> at <hi>Athens:</hi> I alſo am content and prayſe you with others, that you be called <hi>Atticus:</hi> but for you to weare at Rome a Gréekiſhe cloke, I cannot praiſe: For I iudge it a token of lightneſſe, and an argument of folly. So al theſe wryters with all other are good to learne: but euery one in his kinde: for euery one of them had ſome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thing proper vnto himſelfe that beſt lyked hym: which they all of their owne authority might deſently do. Now touching the know ledge of the greateſt matters, that is of God, religion, pietie, charitie, and the reſidue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the vertues and praiſe worthie maners, and of mans ſaluation: what is more godly o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more neceſſarye than thoſe thinges which Moyſes, the Apoſtles, and Prophets wrote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yet may theſe thinges be better bewtified i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> due poliſhing, and the puritie of the Latin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tongue be adioyned therevnto, ſo that the Romaine ſpéeche and Latine eloquence, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not corrupted with Hebrue phraſes: which are in their owne tongue verie pleaſant: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in an other offende the eares, and doe make plaine matters ſéeme obſcure.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18511:12"/>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>Thucidides</hi> and <hi>Herodotus, Xenophon, Polybius, Halicarnaſsius,</hi> and <hi>Herodianus</hi> are to be learned amonge the Gréekes: and among the Romaines <hi>Caeſar, Liuius,</hi> and <hi>Tacitus</hi> ought to be read, and diligently to be vnderſtood: that your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be confirmed, your memory aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and the knowledge of thinges may be increaſed. Chiefly we ought to ſtudy that doctrine which was firſt delyuered from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the Iewes, then after the death of Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame was more cléerely ſet abroade. But alwayes prouyded, that euen as our mindes ought to be clenſed and kept vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and pure by the reading therof: ſo would I wiſhe our tongue ſhould not be hindered but amended thereby: for it is not vngodly, and chiefely in this our age: that our tongue and hart ſhould be pure, cleane, and neate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke: And perhaps, it were much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient that Chriſtes religion ſhould be ſet forth with cumlyneſſe of ſpéeche, than with great and gorgeous buildings of Temples: not that I take no delight in theſe: but for that I am more delyghted with the other
<pb facs="tcp:18511:13"/>kinde of bewtifying, and doe thinke it to be more ſéemely and méete. For as the picture of GOD, which is paynted by an excellent Painter doth more recreate and refreſhe vs, than that which is done by ſuche a one as wanteth ſkill. And the Image of <hi>Ioue</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by <hi>Polycletus</hi> was woont more to mooue the ſenſes: than thoſe which were made by other workemen: ſo alſo when religion and ceremonies haue gotten an eloquent expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: they are more playnely taught, and more bewtifully ſet forth: and thereby the loue and feare of God, which by heauenly power is ſtirred vp in vs, is not ſuffered to abate nor faynt awaye. Wherefore, cyuill knowledge, which moſt beſéemeth a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is greatly furthered by thoſe wryters, whoſe bookes we haue that treate of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, &amp; of maners moreouer by Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as wel Gréeke as Latin: &amp; alſo by expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors of other languages, when time eyther ſerueth or requireth. But ſpecially by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, Doctors, &amp; Hiſtoriographers of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And bicauſe we cal y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ciuil knowledge: which of the Gréekes is tearmed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18511:13"/>whereof <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is to ſay, the ſcience of the lawe is no ſmall part: it is requiſite that agayn we reade thoſe excellent monuments which <hi>Plato</hi> hath written of lawes, and <hi>Tullies</hi> two bookes, treating of the ſame matter. Which being well vnderſtoode, will eaſily inſtruct vs what we ought to iudge, and what to anſwere, when queſtion is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of ſuch matter as Lawyers haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled and ſet forth in wryting. But that you be not troubled with a multitude: neyther hindered with the varietie of languages and handling of manye matters: before I ſhall come to the exerciſe of the tongue, I wyll ſhewe you a way wherin I thinke you muſt walke, that you maye ariue at the place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted. Therfore I will deuide my whole treatiſe into thrée tymes, one in hearing, the other in reading, and the thirde in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and deuiſing. In which thrée, if meaſure be vſed, and the order kept which I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, you ſhall both attayne the thing you labor for: and there ſhal remaine a ſufficient time euery daye, after euery action, to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation of the minde, refection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength,
<pb facs="tcp:18511:14"/>and confirmation of the health: whereof I wiſhe great regarde to be had, bicauſe that the minde is moſt pregnant and freſh when the bodie is in perfite helth, &amp; doth then more quickly apprehende, and ſéeth further, and doth kepe thoſe things more diligently which it hath learned, perceiued, and deuiſed. I wil therefore returne to that, that is propoſed in the firſt place: I meane the tyme of hearing in the which are two kindes of perſons to be conſidered: for both we vſe trachers as <hi>M. Ciceros</hi> ſonne <hi>Cratippus</hi> at Athens: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we haue repeators. And <hi>Cicero</hi> in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Atticus</hi> lamenteth the death of his <hi>Soſitheus,</hi> whom he calleth a pleaſant boye. Writers that be harde to vnderſtande, and ſuch as treat of high matters: muſt be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the handes of thoſe whome we at this daye tearme readers, profeſſours of the tongues and Schoolemaiſters. Of this ſort concerning Philoſophie are <hi>Platos</hi> bookes called <hi>Gorgias</hi> and <hi>Protagoras,</hi> and diuers other of his Dialogues. Such are <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles</hi> firſt bookes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common welth &amp; of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: Such is <hi>Thucidides</hi> among Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18511:14"/>Such is <hi>Lucan</hi> amomg Poetes: For he doth alſo make a wiſe Citizen and a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike gouernour. Such among Orators are <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> and <hi>Tullie:</hi> not for that their ſayings be obſcure, but bicauſe their Arte is ſecret and cloſe. And as the eye ſight is often glimſed by the beames of the Sunne: ſo is the ſharpeneſſe of the witte ſometime dulled with the brightneſſe of the ſentence being amply adourned and beawtifully ſet forth. You may read by your ſelues <hi>Caeſars</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, and <hi>Xenophons, Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Herodians</hi> Emperors, and alſo <hi>Polibius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The office of the repeater is to rehearſe thoſe things both which we haue learned of others as alſo which wée haue read oure ſelues, and it is good ſometime to haue the repeater recite that thing that we meane to reade: and to haue him in fewe wordes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde the darkeſt ſentences which muſt afterwardes be recogniſed of vs both in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and deuiſing. Hitherto haue we ſhewed what ought to be expounded by our tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and what is to be repeated of our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall repeaters. And what we ought to
<pb facs="tcp:18511:15"/>reade our ſelues. Nowe we will declare what order is to be vſed, and what choyſe muſt be made, and what meaſure at all times muſt be kept. That teacher therefore is chiefly to be choſen which profeſſeth the Arte he teacheth: and hath long exerciſed the ſame. It is a peſtilent thing in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities to haue one man a teacher and a learner all at once, and that they ſhoulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to teach who neuer began to learne: the which in my time was ouermuch vſed. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I denie not but there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of goodly wittes, which euen when they learne, are better able to teache, than ſome others that long before haue both learned and taught the ſame. But we ſpeake of that time when choyſe is giuen vs of twaine that we may alwaies elect the beſt learned and of moſt experience. Howbeit if it happen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, we will follow the example of great Capitaines and noble Emperours: who are woont to preferre a valiaunt yong ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour before an olde Cowarde or Crauen. But in the choyſe of two or more: conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration muſt be had, not onely of their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18511:15"/>but alſo of their order in teaching, and facilitie in diſpatching their matters. In the which notwithſtanding, we haue to weighe what is the habilitie of the learner, what ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie he hath, and howe much he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited. When I was at Paris, <hi>Peter Danes</hi> and <hi>Iames Tuſan</hi> atchieued one purpoſe, though by diuers meanes, that they might haue many auditors. They both diſpatched a great number of lines in one howre. <hi>Tuſan</hi> did examine them aptly according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rules of Grammer, and <hi>Danes</hi> did ſo interprete <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> ſo much as was in him to do: and as farre as the tongue woulde giue him leaue, that he made him ſéeme a Romaine, beautified and ſet forth with <hi>Tullies</hi> words and ſentences. Therefore the learned gladly hearde the one: the other had for his ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſuch as woulde from the firſt founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be taught that tongue, of a learned Schoolemaſter: It is a ſigne of great iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and a token of much learning, a ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of diligence, and a ſincere meaning, not to ſtaye longer in teaching a thing than néede requireth: and ouerpaſſe nothing that
<pb facs="tcp:18511:16"/>is to be expounded: as well for the matter as for the wordes and the Arte, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of it with other writers. And thus much touching the teacher. Nowe we haue to ſpeake of the order and choyſe which you muſt vſe: and of the maner and waye which in reading and hearing you ought to folow. Wherein eftſoones I muſt call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the ende of your ſtudies, which is the knowledge of excellent learning, ioyned with an honeſt life, and a well polliſhed ſtile, and a pure and vncorrupt ſpeache, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with ornamentes both of wordes and ſentences.</p>
            <p>And bicauſe you vnderſtande for the moſt part the firſt Artes of ſpeache, and the preceptes and varietie of the two tongues, I meane Gréeke and Latine, wherevnto is ioyned the knowledge of wordes and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for that that wordes are the images of things. Therefore from this time forwarde you muſt ioyne togither and combine the ſtudie of them both: and to that ende tendeth all my talke.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, we will deuide the daye
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18511:16"/>into two parts or times, of which the one is the morning, the other the afternoone. Now as the morning muſt be beſtowed vppon <hi>Tullie</hi> and writinge: the time that remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth after dinner ſhall ſerue for other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, ſuch as may teach vs other good Artes and knowledge. Not as though theſe other Authors were not commended among lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men for their ſtyle and ſpeache: or as though <hi>Tullie</hi> were not full of excellent knowledge, fetched from the verie depth and bottome of Philoſophie and wiſedome. But although they are both helped the one by the other: yet bicauſe I iudge that <hi>Cicero</hi> at all times is chieflye and moſt principally to be followed, when we ſéeke for example: I muſt make this difference, that it maye be vnderſtanded to whome at ſometimes it is lawfull to digreſſe, and from whome it is not lawfull to depart at all. For ſéeing you accept me herein as a teacher, thus thinke with your ſelfe, that ſome thinges there bée which I accoumpt lawfull, wherevnto I giue you leaue to diuert ſometime, and ſome other things which I accompt vnlawfull,
<pb facs="tcp:18511:17"/>wherein if you make default: I ſhall thinke you vnmindefull of this benifite, which you haue receyued at my handes, which is a foule vice in maners, and not to be named. For notwithſtanding that I in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning did only craue of you, temperance, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and conſtancie: yet I will not that the other vertues be neglected of you: and for mine owne part I craue a faithfulneſſe at your handes, and a mindefulneſſe of the councell I giue you: which I account to be the certaine token of thankfulneſſe. And but if you beléeue that I giue true councell, my talke ſhall be but of ſmall authoritie with you. For as much then as a Citie is a ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and fellowſhip of men one with another: and ſéeing no ſocietie is larger: nor is more wider ſpreade through ſo many peoples and nations with an incredible vertue and ſtrength, than the fellowſhip of Chriſtians which is called the Church: to the which felowſhip Ieſu the eternall ſonne of the true God who hath a ſurname of a Kingly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and is named Chriſt, hath called all mankinde out from euery part and corner
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18511:17"/>of the worlde. Sith therefore I ſaye this is the true ſocietie: néedes muſt it bée that ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill knowledge be grounded chiefly on the doctrine of Chriſt and God: and that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man ſhoulde moſt truſt vpon this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, ſéeing it is ordeyned for the obteyning of the heauenly ſocietie, and doth agrée to the heauenly lawes and the gouernement of God. The Philoſophers ſought after this: neyther coulde they finde it: If <hi>Minos</hi> of <hi>Crete,</hi> or <hi>Licurgus</hi> of <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> or <hi>Solon</hi> of <hi>Athens</hi> had knowne this, they had left their Countrie men in more bleſſed eſtate than we ſée they haue. This was vnknowne to <hi>Socrates Plato</hi> his maiſter, to <hi>Plato</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, yea <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> alſo wanted this doctrine to make his ciuill knowledge perfite. Yet I ſay not this to that ende, that they haue not written excellently and well: and that in many places or rather in the moſt part: but bicauſe they were ignorant of that diuinitie, whereby they might call men to heauenly concorde, and bring their Citizens to that ende which they haue purpoſed in their bookes, I meane felicitie, and ſuch a life as
<pb facs="tcp:18511:18"/>is perfite of it ſelfe. And ſurely if theſe things be true, as in déede they are, it is to be thought that there be ſome things which are to be reade all our liues long: and ſome things that once reading ſufficeth, ſo that the memorie decaye not: and ſome thinges which are to be recogniſed at certaine times. Which order you muſt obſerue for euer: and you muſt neyther ſuffer nor bée content to be withdrawne or driuen from it: if ye will continue in that conſtancie, which you promiſed. Religion therefore and the cogitation thereof is perpetually to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. For often times moſt noble, wiſe, and moſt vertuous men, after things done with great glorie, and ſometime after highe honors atchieued by gouerning the common welth, haue left that charge eyther bicauſe of ſickeneſſe, or by reaſon of yeares: who yet from vertue, Religion and the godly ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of their forefathers, coulde not be driuen. And I beléeue that <hi>Cicero</hi> and other Orators good and vertuous men, did not purpoſe alwayes to pleade cauſes in the Court by reaſon of their age: yet they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18511:18"/>neuer to forſake an honeſt life. But alwayes to be doing ſome thing, and as much as they coulde to write of ſuch things in the Latine tongue as might both profite their Countrymen, and pertaine wholye to the ſetting forth of Philoſophie and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in their natiue tongue. Wherefore if Religion in all the life is to be regarded and chiefly when we drawe towarde our ende: &amp; if a wiſe man ought not to caſt awaye the penne out of his hande, we ought perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to acquaint our ſelues with thoſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whoſe ſtyle we are deſirous to follow, and thorowe whome we maye be the better inſtructed, to vertue, Religion, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Now if this may not be denied, then we may conclude that a wiſe man ought to ſpende his life in holy writers: and an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent man ought to be daily conuerſant in <hi>Tullies</hi> workes. For as Religion maketh holie the ſocietie of men, ſo doth eloquence make it pleaſant: and both ioyned togither, cauſe it to be helthfull. To this ſtudie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion I doe ioyne the diſcipline of maners, and all ciuill doctrine and hyſtories: and in
<pb facs="tcp:18511:19"/>this I thinke a wiſe man ought to ende his life. And theſe are thoſe thinges which I déeme worthie to be read and ſtudyed for euer: now ſuch things as it, ſufficeth to read but once, are in this maner to be diſcerned. For what ſoeuer is of that kinde, hath this nature, that eyther it is not worthie to be reade for the fooliſhneſſe thereof, or for the ſhortneſſe, or eaſineſſe not néedefull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate: of theſe two kindes, that which is foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe muſt be ſhunned: And thother which is ſhort and eaſie to vnderſtande and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, muſt be applied to further that ende, wherevnto the varietie of our ſtudie is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred: and is then chiefly to be vſed, when the minde being wearied with the ſtudie of weightyer labors for recreation ſake doth withdraw it ſelfe: and in this refreſhing, it is verie good to haue a repeater whoſe voyce doth ſhowe ſome learning, being cléere and diſtinct that it may be eaſily vnderſtanded: and that the pronunciation maye bréede no lothſomneſſe but rather a pleaſure, which chiefly is to be conſidered of in this time of leyſure and recreation. There remaineth yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18511:19"/>a thirde kinde of writers: I meane thoſe which are ſometimes to be recogniſed, which is done chieflye at two ſeaſons: whereof the one hath an honeſt neceſſitie: of the other, a learned man muſt haue an accoumpt. For it commeth often to paſſe, that writing and reading of ſtories muſt be intermitted for a ſeaſon, when we write any thing of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or when we frame a worke of ſome part of the common welth, or when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe ſome Poeme. When that is done, if we liſt to finiſhe the ſtorie that we haue begoon of ſome certaine time, or of ſome warre, we muſt reſort vnto that Author, whoſe order and maner we meane to followe in vttring our matter, and to whome we woulde be counted lyke. And if after the finiſhing of that worke we be diſpoſed to write of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie: it were good to repaire to the ſame Author from whome we are digreſſed, and whoſe ſteps we meane to follow.</p>
            <p>But for as much as we haue appointed thrée yeares, within which compaſſe this my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſultation is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended, I will now come vnto them: and firſt I will recompt in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:18511:20"/>what thinges they be, wherewith we muſt be furniſhed within this ſpace. For the Latin tongue therfore we muſt know <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> throughout, and <hi>Caeſars</hi> Commentaries, <hi>Saluſt</hi> and <hi>Virgill.</hi> In the which ſtudie if we haue anye time to ſpare, we maye inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingle ſome part of <hi>Plautus, Terence, Varro, Lucret.</hi> and other, ſo much as maye eaſilye be vnderſtoode, and bringeth plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure when we knowe it. In the Gréeke tongue we muſt reade <hi>Xenophons</hi> treatiſe that he wrote of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and the Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries wherein he diſcourſeth of <hi>Socrates,</hi> we muſt reade alſo <hi>Herodotus, Thucidides, Demoſthenes,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> bookes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and of the common welth. Beſide <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> and <hi>Heſiodus.</hi> And when we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenientlye intermit ſome of theſe, we muſt now and then common with <hi>Theocrit,</hi> and <hi>Pinder, Euripides,</hi> and <hi>Sophocles,</hi> or ſome other Philoſophers, or Hyſtorian, or Poet, which ſhall beſt delight vs. But euermore when we ſtudie for knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, we muſt vſe our Logicke rules, whereby we examine and trie the troth. And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18511:20"/>moreouer, we muſt heare the Maiſters and teachers of Geometrie, Coſmographie, and Aſtronomie, ſo farre as ſhall be neceſſarie for the ende of our ſtudie. And we muſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of all theſe, ſtore of matter to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our ſtile, which daily muſt be ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The nature whereof is ſuch that with ydleneſſe and intermiſſion it waxeth blunt, but with exerciſe and as it were with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall earing, euen as the Ploweſharde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth brighter, ſo this is made more ſhining and ſharpe. You ſée the burthen that I haue purpoſed to laye vpon your ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which if you doe carie till the Calends of Ianuarie do this time thrée yeres return againe, we ſhall atchieue the thinge we would: that is, that your talke may be both wiſe and eloquent, and that the tongue and minde may ſounde alyke, which I thinke to be more ſwéeter than any Muſicke. I haue named to you in groſſe, and peraduenture not diſtinctly nor fullye ynough what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours you muſt reade and vnderſtande. Wherefore I will alſo ſpeake a little of this matter before I declare vnto you my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:18511:21"/>on touching obſeruation, imitation, and ſtyle: that you maye in like maner vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande at what time euery one is to be read: and alſo that you maye perceyue what way you ought to take for the perfite vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all theſe Authors, which I haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed you to reade within the time and ſpace prefixt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therfore otherwiſe than we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly doe, we muſt obſerue and follow that auncient &amp; noble rule: that biddes vs to haue a ſpeciall care &amp; regarde of time, and that we make good account of it: &amp; that we our ſelues doe conſtantly continue in diligent reading and hearing of other, which rule if we kepe, we muſt chiefly auoyde thrée kinds of vices: whereof the firſt, is intemperance in eating and drinking: the ſecond, is the vnſeaſonable companying with our friendes, and much conuerſation with ydle perſons: the laſt, is walking abrode. Where of riſeth ſuch incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience that euen thoſe that be painfull and induſtrious by this euill cuſtome in gadding are drawne to ſloth. And they that write of huſbandrie, haue alſo giuen this leſſon, who
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18511:21"/>forbid a Farmour or Bailiffe to be a wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker: yet neuertheleſſe the eye aſwell of the Lorde as of the rich Farmour doth féede the horſe: and where the Maiſter walketh about the worke it cauſeth the workemen to take more paine. Howbeit, bicauſe this cuſtome doth oftentimes deceyue the vnwiſe: it is diligently to be looked vnto againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, leaſt the ſwéeteneſſe of walking doe make vs neglect the time and beguile vs of the care we ſhoulde haue of ſtudie, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe and effeminate good natures, and by deceytefull cuſtome ſhoulde wring good purpoſes out of the mindes &amp; thoughts of thoſe that be ſtudious. For neyther doth the name of the <hi>Peripatickes</hi> driue me from mine opinion, nor mine owne cuſtome moue me that am naturally giuen to walk. But the <hi>Peripatickes</hi> did walke in the time of their diſputing: as for our preceptes they appertaine to reading. And for mine owne part I had done more good and gotten more profite, if I had accuſtomed my ſelfe to ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtill. I lyke not therefore theſe walkes and paces in time of reading (for there are
<pb facs="tcp:18511:22"/>other times for health and recreation) but in recording, or deuiſing, or conferring one with another, I doe not miſlike them, if they be moderately vſed: that after a ſmall walke and within a ſhort time we maye returne to reading againe. Neuertheleſſe, when you are in your ſtudie and haue occaſion to ſerch in many bookes I doe not diſallow that you ſtande at the Deſke. And in conferring of Authors, and comparing many textes togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wée muſt néedes fléete from place to place: But yet as we woulde haue a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in eating, drinking, and in familiar méetings: ſo muſt we here alſo require the like. That we conſider well what is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and what is ynough: whereof the one is meaſured by profite, the other by plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And whatſoeuer doth profitably come in place while we are reading: we doe not refuſe it.</p>
            <p>Now ſith I haue ſhewed you theſe thrée kinde of vices: let vs ſée what is next after to be done. And peraduenture the next is to conſider whether all theſe Authors which I haue named, may if you avoyde and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18511:22"/>theſe thrée vices, be diſpatched by you in theſe thrée yeares, and in what time that may be done. For the times are to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, like as men doe meaſure euerye action, not onely by that which is done, but alſo by the ſpace of time wherein it was a doing, we will therefore begin with religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to which we attribute the firſt and laſt howre of the day. And there is no doubt, but in theſe two howres within thrée yeares ſpace, we may be able to vnderſtand and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member much that ſhall be commodious for our inſtruction in religion, and for the framing of a Chriſtian and godly life. Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when as our ſtyle ſhall be the better fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with matter taken out of the holye writers, ſo that of good Latine wée maye make better, and for the Gréeke we maye eyther interprete it into pure Latine, or ſo handle and poliſh it, that there may appeare ſome goodly matter, and yet men ſhould not eſpie from whence it commeth: or if it bée eſpied, it ſhould ſéeme more beawtifull, and beare a ſhewe of greater learning. Theſe thrée times I ſaye, of reading and writing,
<pb facs="tcp:18511:23"/>will bréede in a man ſtore and varietie of matter, and as well for religion as other learning, though he haue but a meane wit, ſo that he ioyne thervnto continuall helpe of diligence. The other howres in the morning I aſſigne to <hi>Ciceros</hi> workes, and to the ſtile, not doubtinge but <hi>Tullie</hi> maye be all read and vnderſtoode in thrée yeares, which if it be graunted, this is alſo true, that in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternone howres as much maye be gotten out of other writers as well in the Gréeke as in the Latine tongue: beſides thoſe bookes which ſhall be recited by the repeater, of whom we haue ſpoken before. Wherefore theſe thrée yeares ſpace ſhall bring great knowledge of religion: and of a great part of Philoſophie in <hi>Tullie</hi> beſides, many en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples and hyſtories of his time, which in his Epiſtles and Orations are learned: and further al kind of ſentences, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, déedes, &amp; ſayings. And all this may be done with the mornings traueyle, which ſhall neyther be great, nor yet vnpleaſant if order and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be obſerued. Now the afternones ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſhall giue and yéelde as much matter out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18511:23"/>of <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato, Demoſthenes, Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon, Herodotus, Thucidides, Homer, Heſiod, Euripides, Sophocles, Pindar:</hi> and out of the other Orators and Gréeke Poets: alſo out of the Latine, as <hi>Caeſar, Saluſt, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Vergil, Lucretius, Catullus, Horas,</hi> and though you ioyne none other to theſe, yet you eaſily perceyue how much learning and variety may be gotten out of them. Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, I wiſhe no writer to be ouerpaſſed: but that we taſte ſomewhat of his doings, and runne ouer ſome part of him, and diligently obſerue ſome things in him. But yet in ſuch wiſe that we haue care and regarde of the time, with due conſideration of the thrée yeare, and of the ende of our ſtudie which we haue appointed. And for this cauſe ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue I named all writers: neyther bid I you to reade all theſe: neither forbid I you to knowe thoſe which I haue not named. <hi>Plautus</hi> is a pure Romaine Poet: and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> a Poet by nature both plentifull and neate: and both the <hi>Plinies</hi> very profitable, and <hi>Liui</hi> is a loftie writer of an hiſtorie: and <hi>Tacitus</hi> is a true reporter of things. And as
<pb facs="tcp:18511:24"/>for thoſe that haue written of huſbandrye, building, and of warfare: who denieth but a learned man ſhoulde be acquainted with them: but my preſcription is of thrée yeare: and is agreable to your age, calling, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie. For I write this worke for your ſake: wherein I conſider what maner of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man I would traine vp, that may be méete to be a counceller of Emperors and Kings, and to haue gouernement in the common welth. And yet neuertheleſſe I doe not doubt if you get thoſe thinges which you ought partly to vnderſtande, and partly to haue in memorie, as well out of holye writers, as out of all <hi>Cicero:</hi> and out of the beſt Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> and out of the bookes of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> written of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth and of lawes, and out of thoſe which I brieflye named a little before: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you may ouerſlippe ſome of them if the time ſo require: neuertheleſſe I ſaye if with care and order you atchieue but onely theſe thinges, I doubt not but you ſhall be welcome to euery learned companie, and to euery wiſe aſſemblie: no leſſe than <hi>Cotta</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18511:24"/>and <hi>Sulpitius</hi> were acceptable auditors to <hi>Sceuola, Craſſus,</hi> and <hi>Antonius</hi> in their thrée diſcourſes of an Orator: euen as <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> was glad alſo of the companie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yong man <hi>Triarius</hi> in his diſputation that he had with <hi>Torquatus</hi> concerning the endes of good and euill. But it is nowe time that I come to the order of reading and writing, which is the principall part of this our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For now all men knowe almoſt what Authors are ſpecially to be read, and what euery one may reade to his moſt vtilitie and profit: but how they ought to be read: Firſt, fewe men knowe: ſecondlye, thoſe that knowe are of diuers iudgements. For as he ſayth, howe many heades, ſo many wittes. But I will declare my opinion as I thinke beſt, and after mine owne maner, chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging nothing as proper to my ſelfe, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue vſed as well as I: and leauing to euery one his owne iudgement. Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you, not bindinge others to theſe my precepts. Now in reading we ought ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to follow the ſame order, which we vſe in writing and ſpeaking: that firſt, we care
<pb facs="tcp:18511:25"/>for things and matter: then after for words. But as in deuiſing and writing we are firſt to conſider what we will teache, defende, or vtter: and then by what meanes we maye attaine thereto: ſo in readinge we muſt runne ouer the whole Booke, or Oration, or Epiſtle, or ſome whole worke: and after we muſt take in hande by péecemeale to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and iudge, and weigh euery poynt, leaſt any thing ſhould eſcape our vnderſtanding, without the which, all memory is weak, and obſeruation is vncertaine, and imitation is deceytfull, although it is true that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we méete with ſome places in olde and auncient writers, which are of ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie and ſo obſcure that they cannot be vnderſtoode at all, or elſe after they be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded, the profite thereof is not worth the paynes: ſuch places doe I thinke beſt to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpaſſe. I remember that being a yong ſtudent at Loueine, and reading at home in my Chamber the Oration of <hi>Tullie</hi> for <hi>Roſcius:</hi> I lightly paſſed ouer the allegorie of the Seruilian Lake: but when I pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely interpreted that Oration at Paris, I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18511:25"/>indeuoured all that I coulde to expounde the ſame Allegorie, hauing before aſked <hi>Budes</hi> councell and aduiſe therein. Yet I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that I then gaue this councell alſo to my auditors, that if they fortuned to méete with the like rockes and obſcure places, they ſhould doe as good Plowmen doe, as well in ſéede time as in harueſt, who are woont both in plowing and reaping to ouerpaſſe the thornie thickets, and déepe rootes of trées, and craggie ſtones, if the coſt ſurmount the fruite. So alſo ſtudentes ſhoulde note thoſe places which cannot profitablye be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode at the firſt reading or preſent time. Neuertheleſſe, as huſbandemen ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ſtones, and digge vp ſtumpes of trées, and plucke vp thornes when they can ſo doe, and when any gaine maye come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: ſo alſo it is good for ſtudents to ſtaye at thoſe ſentences which may be vnderſtoode, although with ſome hardneſſe, ſpecially if they bring light vnto the reſt, which without them woulde be obſcure. Therefore the firſt traueyle of reading doth conſiſt in theſe two poyntes: the next, touching order and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb facs="tcp:18511:26"/>of thinges: the thirde concerneth the handling of the matter. In placing we note what is firſt ſet, as in a ſhewe or the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front of a battaile, and what is reſerued to the ende, and what is handſomly conueyed into the middeſt. In handling wée obſerue what is largely diſcourſed, what is ſhortlye diſcuſſed, and howe oft any thing is repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that with what kindes of wordes and formes of ſentences: moreouer, after what waye and maner of methode. In theſe poyntes conſiſteth the whole reaſon or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of vnderſtanding, of imitating, of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, of ſpeaking: to the atteyning whereof, we muſt prouide thrée kinde of Bookes, the one for things and matter, which are called the bookes of common places as may repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the preceptes of Arte. The places of things and words are almoſt one: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding howe they differ, I haue declared in other bokes. The places of Arte are taken from thence, from whence we learned the rules and preceptes of the ſame, which of all other are beſt ſet forth by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Cicero.</hi> Now this practiſe is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18511:26"/>conſiſteth in reſolution, whereof you haue hearde me ſpeake oftentimes: which prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe we ought to begin in our yong yeares: but we muſt continually exerciſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly go forward in the ſame, if we meane to follow thoſe Gréekes &amp; Romaines which haue bene prayſed for learning, and haue bene counted wiſe in gouernment, I meane not only Rhetoricians, or Orators, or Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, but alſo Conſuls, Emperors, and Kinges: who haue nowe no leſſe fame and glorie through learning, than they haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned by their notable and valiant déedes. Wherefore the barbarous cuſtome and ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall opinion of our Gentlemen is the more to be blamed. Who for the moſt part thinke themſelues not worthie to bée accounted ſouldiers, nor warlike ynough, if they ſéeme ſkilfull in letters, who are aſhamed of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and not of maners, what maners I meane, ſpeciallye in ſome of them, I am aſhamed to report. How much more is it to be prayſed when in a noble houſe there be noble Gentlemen, whoſe liues and learning are aunſwereable to their birth and nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<pb facs="tcp:18511:27"/>Who as they take enſample of a noble and commendable life, eyther of their owne elders, or of better houſes: ſo doe they giue an enſample of the lyke to their poſteritie that ſhall ſuccéede them, and encourage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men to follow their vertuous ſteppes. What did more hinder the true glorie of the noble Athenian <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> than that he fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed not the councell and good leſſons of <hi>Socrates. Pericles</hi> in the ſame common welth obteyning great prayes and high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noume, hath to thanke eloquence and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the greateſt part thereof. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines enuied and had in great hatred the newe vſurped kinde of tyrannie of <hi>Iulius Caeſar:</hi> yet is he the leſſe enuied therefore, &amp; the leſſe diſprayſed of honeſt men, by reaſon of his bookes which are called his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries: wherein is expreſſed his Martiall proweſſe, which is no more renoumed by his valiant doinges, than adorned and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily ſet forth by his excellent writing. But that I may returne thither from whence I am digreſſed: it behoueth vs to haue theſe thrée kindes of volumes whereof I haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18511:27"/>ſpoken. That is to wéete, of thinges, of wordes, and of Arte. And notwithſtanding, there be all readie ſet forth many Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of the Latine tongue: and though ſome men alſo haue indeuoured to gather togither common places of thinges, and to ſtore vs therewithall: yet is it both profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for memorie: and the gayneſt waye to perfection that euery man ſhould gather and diſpoſe his owne places whereby he ſhall haue occaſion to adde or detract, or chaunge ſomething in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuentions of others. And for bicauſe I haue often both ſpoken &amp; written at other times of the places of words, which are almoſt all one with the receptacles of things: it ſhall not néede at this time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate the ſame. As for the places of Arte they are gathered out of the bookes of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricians: as for example, concerning the partes of an Oration, and the kindes as well of cauſes as of reaſons and Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call figures, and Periodes. And bicauſe the obſeruation of theſe things pertayneth to the ſecond labor of reading wherof, we began a little ſince to ſpeak: and bicauſe the times of
<pb facs="tcp:18511:28"/>reading, obſeruing and noting, ought to bée ioyned and knit togither: we will declare ſomewhat more at large this maner of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing and noting. This practiſe I nowe ſpeake off, beginnes with marking, and endes with compariſon. I call marking, that which the Gréekes terme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when we conſider and vnderſtande as well the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as the handling thereof. Likewiſe I call compariſon as the Gréekes woulde ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Which is when we compare one thing with an other, to ſée how eyther they agrée or differ. For firſt we haue to conſider what is ſayd, and how it is ſayd: Then after foraſmuch as one thing hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a ſundrie kinde of handling, for comely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake, the preſent things are to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with other, which are written and ſet forth eyther by the ſame Author, or by ſome other. After this bypartite and double labor we muſt go to noting, and looke what we haue marked and vnderſtoode, we muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the ſame to our places of Arte, and note it in our bookes, diſtinguiſhing euery thing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18511:28"/>as it were in the proper formes and ſeates. Againe there are thrée kindes of noting, one when we write out whole places, another when we gather the ſumme of the ſame places in fewe wordes, which the Grecians call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we may terme them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgements. The thirde kinde is when we drawe out euery part in figures, which for the more playnneſſe in teaching I am wont to call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is to ſaye figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue draughts, or if I might ſo terme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, defigurations. For figurations doe more properlye pertaine to the Authors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: our draughtes may aptlier be called defigurations. Neyther is this a toy deuiſed by vs, but a certaine thing which hath bene long ſince vſed in Gréece and Italie of the maiſters of Logicke and Rhetoricke there. For both the <hi>Peripatickes</hi> diſtinguiſh their kindes of concluſions and the contrarietie of Propoſitions by figures: and likewiſe the Rhetoricians call their Periodes of thrée members, ſome of them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which haue all thrée partes of equall length, and ſome of them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which haue onelye
<pb facs="tcp:18511:29"/>two parts of like equalitie: Likewiſe when Orators and other writers diuerſly ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie matters, as a man would ſaye, exedifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or buildinges. And in the ſeconde of thoſe thrée bookes which <hi>Tullie</hi> entituled <hi>De Oratore,</hi> that is to ſaye, an Orator. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie maketh mention of framinge and buildinge of an hyſtorie, bicauſe all theſe thinges maye be drawne out and framed as buildinges are: that the foundation maye appeare, the roofe may ſhewe forth, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunces may be ſéene, the Chambers may be ſeuered, and that the doores, windowes, pillers, and other partes may cunningly be ſet before our eyes, ſo that the whole buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding may be vewed. The like whereof, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillus</hi> and <hi>Sceuola</hi> did note alſo in <hi>Albutius</hi> and <hi>Craſſus</hi> in the building of their wordes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>How feately are theſe wordes ſet out,</l>
               <l>As pauing stones by Arte no doubt:</l>
               <l>In beautie braue, and colour gaye,</l>
               <l>Thy bostes and bragges doe then awaye.</l>
               <l>My ſonne in lawe fine Craſsus is:</l>
               <l>Is thy Rhetoricke as pure as his?</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18511:29"/>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p>The like maner of practiſe maye be vſed in
<pb facs="tcp:18511:30"/>Periodes of two or foure members, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in long ſentences, or circumductions, of the which, you haue hearde in Rhetoricke, neyther were it harde for me to bring many enſamples, if the Printers woulde giue me leaue, or were it appertayning to this place. For in déede this treatiſe requireth an other time: and it is ynough that I now ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you this order a farre of. Chieflye ſith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time you haue hearde me tell you of the like. Howbeit, not only Periodes and long ſentences may be thus figured, but we maye in like ſort note in Orators the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of thinges, which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> This Sommer I expounded vnto you the Eclogs of <hi>Vergill:</hi> and I ſhewed you how artificially and finely poore <hi>Melobeus</hi> ſorow and miſerie was expreſſed in verſe. For the firſt foure verſes haue a compariſon: but how trimly are they handled, how cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are they framed and ſet togither.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O happie art thou Tityrus,</l>
               <l>that vnder Beechen tree,</l>
               <l>Thy ſong in Pipe of ſlender Ote,</l>
               <l>doste ſounde with voyce ſo free.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18511:30"/>
            <p>He ſingeth the felicitie of <hi>Tityrus</hi> in two verſes: but of himſelfe he complaineth in a verſe and a halfe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>But we al as our countrie costes and pleaſant fields forſake.</l>
               <l>We flie our natiue ſoyle.</l>
            </q>
            <p>After, he returneth to the happineſſe of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrus,</hi> and finiſheth the vnperfite verſe and addeth the whole.</p>
            <q>
               <l>But thou in ſhade thy caſe doste take,</l>
               <l>And makest the woods for to reſounde aloude faire Amarill.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This expoſition hath a compaſſe in maner of a circle: for euen as in words, ſo likewiſe in things there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is to ſay a circle, or a circlelik hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſetting forth of the matter. Therfore they that followe the Mathematickes doe note this with a circle: yet may it alſo well ynough be marked with this figure.</p>
            <figure/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18511:31"/>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Melobeus</hi> at <hi>Tityrus</hi> beginneth and at him alſo endeth. But peraduenture ſome man will demaunde what commoditie is in this deuiſe and practiſe: ſéeing it is not only long, but alſo almoſt infinite, and beſides it is frée and at the libertie of the writer. And that I may firſt make aunſwere to the laſt poynt: that it is not algates free, nor at the writers libertie, that ought both to ſatiſfie the eares of the hearers, and the iudgement of the learned, and muſt be agréeable to the matter. Secondly, although there be infinite examples (for manye are extant, moe haue decayed, and many new peraduenture ſhall be inuented) yet is the order of this practiſe comprehended and limitted within certayne formes: euen as this compariſon is whereof we ſpeake, which is eyther of like things, or of contrarie thinges, or of things that differ in ſome pointes. Furthermore, eyther both partes are ſhortened or inlarged alyke: or one part more than an other, or the firſt part is againe repeated in the ende as we ſée for example in this beginning of <hi>Vergil.</hi> And as it is not the firſt part of a Maiſter Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18511:31"/>to vewe and know all the buildings that are in the worlde, but it ſufficeth him to haue ſuruayde and taken a patterne of ſome of the beſt in euery kinde: ſo alſo ought a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to doe: that amongſt a number he make choyſe of ſome, whom he may followe, and with whome he maye contende at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Now touching the commoditie hereof, the firſt profite is this, that we ſhall hereby the better vnderſtande the matter, and ſo kéepe it the longer in memorie: the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the Arte or workemanſhip bréedeth a pleaſure, wherof riſeth a conſtancie and an earneſt deſire to read other mens writings: which two vertues are repugnant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto other two vices: I meane light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and lothſomneſſe, than the which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more peſtilent and pernicious to honeſt ſtudie. Thirdly, this diligence doth much helpe iudgement: and oftentimes the marking of the Arte in an eaſie place ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs more able to fetche out the déepe and hidden ſenſe of harder places. As <hi>Tityrus</hi> in his Antiſtrophe or Counterverſe in the firſt verſe he acknowledgeth both God and his
<pb facs="tcp:18511:32"/>owne quiet ſtate.</p>
            <q>O Melibey our God to vs this quiet ſtate did will.</q>
            <p>After he rendreth a reaſon thereof in two verſes, and promiſeth to honor him as God.</p>
            <q>
               <l>For he, for aye ſhall be my God, vpon his Altar ſtone</l>
               <l>Oft ſhall the tender Lambe bee ſlaine from ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foldes of our owne.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In the two laſt verſes he returneth agayne to his quiet ſtate, whereof he had ſpoken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and declares wherein it conſiſteth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>He did permit my beastes to graze at randon as you ſee,</l>
               <l>And bade me play on homely Pipe what best deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mee.</l>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>There is yet alſo a further profite of this practiſe conſiſting aſwell in thoſe Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18511:32"/>which I called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgements, as in theſe Apoſchematiſmes, which we engliſhed figuratiue draughts or defigurations: and that profite is this, that hereby we perceyue how the kynds of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king differ one from another, and by what meanes we may attayne to diſcerne euerye kinde, for without this practiſe, wherby ſhall we iudge how the thrée beginninges of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gils</hi> works differ one from another: I meane of this Eclog, of this Georgiks, and of his <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neidos.</hi> For this firſt beginning of this Eclog is finely compact by reaſon of the compariſon that he vſeth, which agréeth well to the ſongs of the ſhepeherdes: the ſeconde beginning is moderately inlarged by particion, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemeth a good ſparing fellow of the countrie, and a thriftie huſbandman: the thirde, is ſet forth and adorned in ample maner, as the grauitie of a noble perſonage did require. And theſe thrée kindes may be as well diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by diuerſitie of lines, as by different wordes and termes of Arte: wherefore, this practiſe bringeth this commoditie, that though thinges differ but a verie little, yet
<pb facs="tcp:18511:33"/>wherein they differ, we may plainely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue. For theſe two Latine verſes haue like féete as Grammarians terme them.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Tityre tu patulae recubans ſub tegmine fagi,</l>
               <l>Protenus aeger ago, hanc etiam vix Tityre duco.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which I put into Engliſh in this ſort.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O happie art thou Tityrus that vnder Beechen tree.</l>
               <l>I ſicke doe driue my Gotes a farre, ſcant able this to leade.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Yet doe they differ both in the coniunction of the wordes and letters, and alſo in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie and tune. Whereof ſpringeth the Poeticall number, and that may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded by this draught.</p>
            <p>!.. .!. .!. .. !.. !.</p>
            <p>For the firſt foote and the laſt haue ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harmonie and time. For the ſounde of the voyce is in the firſt ſillable, that is to ſaye, in the thirde ſillable from the ende: and the ſeconde and thirde foote haue the ſounde in the middeſt. But in this verſe it is otherwiſe.</p>
            <q>Protenus aeger ago, hanc etiam vix Tityre duco.</q>
            <p>For though it be meaſured with the lyke
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18511:33"/>féete, yet doth it differ in the ſound &amp; placing of the letters, as appeareth in this draught.</p>
            <p>! .. !. ! ! !. .! ! .. !.</p>
            <p>For the firſt and ſeconde heroicall féete hath two ſharpe ſoundes: and the thirde hath a contraction of vowels: and the two ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daicall féete are more ſounding: ſo that this verſe as it is in matter more dolefull than the firſt: ſo is it alſo grauer in ſounde. Theſe examples are taken out of the Poetes: but bicauſe I interpreted and ſhewed you theſe foreſaide things this laſt ſommer: I purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to vſe ſuch examples as you were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die acquainted withall, and as you had late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hearde. The ſame order we ought to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in Orators and Hyſtorians. For all writers haue amonge themſelues manye thinges in common. As for example, if I woulde thus frame a ſentence: <hi>A wiſe man alwayes followeth honeſtie, and for the maintenance thereof doth willingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelfe to the death, but a foole eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teemeth pleaſure more than honeſtie. Whereas a wiſe man meaſureth not his
<pb facs="tcp:18511:34"/>pleaſure by the wanton delight of the ſenſes, but by vertue and honeſtie.</hi> This kinde of ſpeach or ſentence is philoſophicall: but it is framed according to the paterne that we tooke of the Poet: which thing ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can not be done, or can hardlye be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued without this Arte, practiſe, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, or elſe howſoeuer you lyſt to terme it. And this ſentence differeth from <hi>Vergils</hi> verſes, in kinde and nature of wordes, but in forme and ſhape, it is almoſt all one.</p>
            <p>For as two cotes differ the one from the other, which are ſhaped both of one faſhion, the one being gréene and of a freſh and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant colour: the other blacke and more ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the one hath an elle of cloth more or leſſe than the other, at the diſcretion of the Tayler. To obſerue theſe things, and to ſet them in order in their proper places (doth greatly helpe vs to practiſe &amp; imitate) and of it ſelfe is verie pleaſant to vnderſtande. And although it be variable and copious: yet by beſtowing one howre diligently euery daye where neyther wit nor teacher wanteth: it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18511:34"/>is wonderfull howe much mans traueyle maye atchieue and attaine vnto in thrée yeares ſpace. But dulye conſidering your condicion of life, and what your calling is: I councell you chieflye to beſtowe this your traueyle firſt in the Orations of <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Demoſthenes:</hi> Secondly in <hi>Tullies</hi> bookes of philoſophie and in hyſtories, although alſo his epiſtles are euen at the firſt to be taken in hande. In reading all theſe betwixt times we muſt make a ſteppe to Poets. Howbeit, it muſt be done, ſparingly, neyther may wée tary in them ouer longe before our ſtyle be made both copious and méete for an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. For, I lyke well the councell of Anthonie in <hi>Tullie,</hi> who did diligently and vſually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe himſelfe in ciuill controuerſies, and matters of Court: Hyſtories he read for his pleaſure: and as for Philoſophers, although he read them, yet he did not follow them, by reaſon of their ſhort and briefe diſputations: But from Poets he vtterlye abſtayned, as from thoſe that ſpake in a ſtraunge tongue. Howbeit, Anthonie did much diſſemble his ſtudie, as he did alſo his Arte in pleading.
<pb facs="tcp:18511:35"/>And whereas he ſayeth he vnderſtoode not Philoſophers: nor dealed not with Poetes: he doth declare, what is to be followed in imitating, and what is to be ſhunned, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of an Orator, whoſe talke ought to bée liked and allowed of the people. And I write this to the ende, that you maye ſée in what thinges you ought chiefly to beſtowe your traueyle: whereby you might come vnto that ende which you ſhoote at. But nowe bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all obſeruation, and all noting and marking of examples is prepared for the ſtyle, and is directed and referred vnto wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and other exerciſes: hereafter we are to treate what order in writing you ought to follow. Wherein this is the firſt precept that you conſider well the Argument and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereof you will write, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That ſame muſt be ſuch as we muſt fully and perfitely vnderſtand, neyther can it be that we ſhould in writing expreſſe any maner of thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we know the nature thereof: no more than if a Paynter woulde paynt the buckler of <hi>Aiax,</hi> or the Armour of <hi>Achylles,</hi> or the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18511:35"/>honorable méeting and giftes of <hi>Diomed</hi> and <hi>Glaucus</hi> which he had neuer ſéene, no neuer hearde of. Therefore let this be the firſt precept, that the whole nature of the thinge be knowne. Out of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept riſeth another, that is, that we make choyſe of things: that in the beginning of this our exerciſe we chooſe ſuch matter, as maye be eaſily vnderſtoode and handled and vttered without any tediouſneſſe. For in tediouſneſſe when thinges be long and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, it is to be feared leaſt the traueyle ſhoulde be to painefull and laborſome for a yong beginner, wherof riſeth a lothſomneſſe of this practiſe, which we wiſhe to be delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pleaſant, and not heauie or lumpiſh. For as he ſingeth not ſo well that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to ſing: ſo alſo he writeth not ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly and ſkilfullye which is loth and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to write, as he which writeth with a prompt and earneſt deſire: Therefore the ſtyle is to be applied in the beginning to plaine thinges, and not to thoſe that be tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and obſcure. To which two preceptes is ioyned a thirde, and that is that our matter
<pb facs="tcp:18511:36"/>may be quickly diſpatched: for I will haue the diligence of this practiſe meaſured by the number of lynes, and not by the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the matter. This rule alſo may well be giuen in this place: that the firſt yeare be ſpent in <hi>Cicero,</hi> out of whom, we gather matter for the ſtyle: neyther doe I meane that we ſhould write whole Orations to the imitation of him: but firſt ſome ſmall parts, ſuch as be of the ſhorter ſort. Which haue either ſome neceſſarie, or ſome notable place in them. I call that neceſſarie that is almoſt euer to be vſed: notable, which is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for that it is ſeldome vſed, bicauſe of the ſinguler fineneſſe and paſſing ſhowe, and in longer matters doth not appeare. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we account the firſt yere for the reading of <hi>Tullies</hi> bookes and for the framing of our ſtyle: as for other writers, as well Gréeke as Latine, it ſhall be ſufficient for the time, if we only reade them to vnderſtande them. And let this yeare be onely beſtowed vppon Orators and Proes: the other two yeares that follow may ioyne therewithall Hyſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Poeticall exerciſes, ſo it be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18511:36"/>done, that the other principall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe be not hindered, nor the ſenatorie and Courtlike ſpeache of an Orator be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and corrupted vnawares, eyther with vnwoonted exerciſes of Hyſtorians, or with ſtraunge tongues and termes of Poetes. Now all this they ſhall moſt eaſily and moſt ſurely obteyne, who haue inſtructors to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and teache them: And bicauſe there are fewe which can doe it, we muſt diligentlye take héede, leaſt in ſtede of a learned and a ſkilfull teacher, we prouide one that hath neyther learning nor ſkill.</p>
            <p>And thus much touching the ſtile and the vſe of writing: whervnto the auncient men ioyned meditations and declamations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they woulde deale with ciuill cauſes, and matters in Court. But bicauſe al theſe things without imitation are to no purpoſe, we are from henceforth to ſpeake of that, wherein theſe queſtions may be demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. What is Imitation, and what authors are to be as examples and patternes for to imitate: and whether we ought to take en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample of one, or of many: moreouer, what
<pb facs="tcp:18511:37"/>things are to be imitated, and how: laſtly, at what time we ſhoulde beginne this imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Of all which poyntes I will ſhewe you mine opinion, and that briefely. For in this ſmall volume, and to ſatiſfie your purpoſe it is not ſéemelye to diſcourſe at large of all theſe matters. I doe not teach what is requiſite for all Imitators to doe: but what way you ought to take: who both in nobleneſſe of birth, and in ſtate &amp; calling differ from other learned men, that purpoſe onely to ſpende their lyfe in learning. I call Imitation that which the Gréekes name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wherin is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is to ſay, an ardent deſire and loue to attayne to that in the Oration and ſpeache of an other, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth worthie of prayſe and admiration. And is nothing elſe but a meanes and way howe to expreſſe in your owne talke thoſe maners and formes of ſpeaking: which the Gréekes call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and beautifull in the talke of an other. We will haue an Arte to be in this practiſe, that nothing be done contrarie to comlineſſe, which is to be obſerued wyth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18511:37"/>great care, and there is in it a ſcience of an vniuerſall thing, and of all things: and not of ſome one thing or one parte alone. For who doth commende that paynter, which onely can paynt the hande of a man and not the other partes: or that can onely drawe the heades of men: and cannot repreſent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liuing creatures with méete and apte colours and conuenient ſhadowes. This practiſe requireth no ſmall arte nor ſlender ſcience: but in this doctrine is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued whatſoeuer is requiſite to all kindes of eloquent ſpéech: to the which, all imitation is to be referred, and hereby we may the better vnderſtande the ſeconde queſtion: to wéete, who is moſt chiefly to be imitated, whome we may count for an enſample and patterne to followe. For he whoſe vertues are moſt in number and greateſt in excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, ought chiefly to ſtirre vp our deſires to attayne to the lyke: not that theſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications are ſo to be applyed, that euery man may eaſilye perceyue them: but I ſpeake of you and ſuch as be Imitatours, who can ſpie and diſcerne theſe kindes of
<pb facs="tcp:18511:38"/>Rhetoricall ſpeaches, and the figures of the ſame, though other men can not ſée them. But foraſmuch as amongſt the Latine wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I meane thoſe olde Romaines, whoſe ſpéech was both rounde, pure, and eloquent, there is none that hath more plainelye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to vs all theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and formes of ſpeaking then <hi>Marcus Cicero:</hi> and ſéeing that both the writers of his time, and alſo thoſe that did afterwarde ſuccéede him, haue yelded vnto him the chief price of eloquence: who can doubt, but he ought to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as the ſtandardbearer in all examples. There is no forme either of Rhetorical elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: or of phiſicall diſcourſe, or of dayly ſpéech, but that he hath eyther wholy expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, or he hath left ſuch a draught of ſome part of it, that a meane workeman may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceyue how the other partes ſhoulde be deuiſed and framed. Therefore let this be graunted as a certaine principle, that in the latine tongue there is no enſample ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more certayne, or more excellent than this writer: but let vs ſée alſo whether he be the onely example, and whether other be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18511:38"/>not excellent as well as he. In the which queſtion, if a man will demaunde this of me, whether <hi>Tullie</hi> hath written of all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or no, and whether all his writings are yet extaunt: I muſt néedes ſay that I am demaunded that which neyther can be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, nor ought to be aſked. For wée want his bookes, intituled of a common welth, as all Gramarians doe knowe: wée haue no hyſtories written by him: neyther wrote he any of thoſe thinges which <hi>Varro</hi> hath written of huſbandrie, or <hi>Plinie</hi> of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall things, or <hi>Vegetius</hi> of warfare, or <hi>Vitruuius</hi> of buildings. Furthermore, how many things are there in the Gréeke Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, and Hyſtorians, which <hi>Tullie</hi> hath not touched: but we ſpeake of the ſcience of imitation, which onely maketh a perfite Artes man, and is the Moderatris and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the ſtyle: although the ſtyle it ſelfe is called the maker and maiſter of ſpeaking. I permit that all Authors and all thinges he read: but with diſcretion and iudgement: hauing alwaye this opinion, that we maye gather great ſtore of good matter out of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:18511:39"/>writers, yea, and wordes alſo: but the ſtyle whereof we ſpake being an imitator of the beſt examples, ſhould euer vſe a choyſe, and ſhould applie ſuch formes as are moſt agréeable to the things: the kindes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the which formes can be founde no where better than in <hi>Tullies</hi> workes. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I ought to confeſſe, and gladly doe confeſſe that there be ſome thinges in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes,</hi> the like whereof you cannot ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily finde in <hi>Cicero.</hi> And in <hi>Platos</hi> dialogues there are many notable and diuine thinges worthie imitation, whereof though <hi>Tullie</hi> haue ſhewed nowe and then a ſhadowe, yet hath he expreſſed no perfite ymage. Beſides, who woulde denie that, as if we had verſes to make, we ſhould imitate a Poet: ſo if we had an Hyſtorie to write, we ſhoulde make choyſe of ſome Hyſtorian, wyth whome we might contende, endeuoring to come as neare as we coulde to his patterne and y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. How is it then? verily looke what or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der muſt be kept in reading, the ſame muſt be obſerued in imitation. The firſt and chiefe trauell muſt be beſtowed in <hi>Cicero,</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18511:39"/>whatſoeuer he wanteth, we muſt ſéeke for it in other places. But firſt learne <hi>Tullie,</hi> and exerciſe your ſelfe in him: and ſo long as you go forwarde and finde profite, repent not of your example. I made mention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of comparing of writers, which the Grecians call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which practiſe doth much profite our ſtudies. Who denieth that <hi>Tullie</hi> and <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> doe handle and ſet forth many thinges often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in like ſort, and oftentimes alſo who doth not think it lawdable when you find in other writers that which is good and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, to note and marke the ſame: and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it to the places of Arte and imitation, whereof I haue ſpoken: thereto drawe out the handling of the matter, to name the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and to gather in briefe that thing which is treated off. Therefore ſith our queſtion is of the Latine ſpeeche, and our purpoſe is to polliſh and file the tong &amp; voice of a Senator or counſeller: and ſéeing alwayes we make chiefeſt account of <hi>Cicero:</hi> neyther hath any man expreſſed ſo plentifull the kindes and formes of ſpeache with all elegancie and
<pb facs="tcp:18511:40"/>comelyneſſe of talke as hath this Author: who will ſay that he is not worthie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned and imbraced ſo long as we learne of him excellent matters, and ſuch as we knewe not before, and ſo long as we finde in him euen what we can wiſhe or deſire: and yet were it a madneſſe not to take of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers if we may, that which wanteth in him. Neuertheleſſe, after that you be well furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the ſtore, welth, and ſubſtaunce of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tor, if you happen to come vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> it ſhall not be harde to ſée what you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and what is néedefull for you. And after your taſte is well ſeaſoned with the holeſome lyquors of his eloquence, there ſhall be leſſe daunger and leſſe cauſe to feare that the ſame ſhoulde be corrupted with other ſtraunge matters. Wherefore, after we are acquainted with <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> that ſtronge brawned Orator, we may profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye go to the fine and neate writer <hi>Iſocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes:</hi> or elſe we may ioine them both togither at one time. In like maner, I doe not onely permit you to make an orderly paſſage from <hi>Tullie</hi> to <hi>Demoſthenes:</hi> but alſo I coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18511:40"/>and wiſhe you, betwixt times, to make ſtartes from the one to the other, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to compare the one with the other: and euen ſo, if we purpoſe to write a ſtorie, we muſt vſe another kinde of ſtyle than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we did: which is alſo <hi>Tullies</hi> opinion and iudgement.</p>
            <p>For, a ſtorie is written in a ſofte and trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table kinde of ſtile, as Anthonie ſayth: and flowing with a certayne gentle equabilitie: as contrariwiſe, in the Court and at the barre we ſpeake more roughly, and our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences are more ſharpe and poynant. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an hyſtorie requireth an other kinde of enditing, as we may ſée and perceiue in the beſt authors. But neuertheleſſe, to attayne to this grace no man can better further vs nor furniſh vs then <hi>Tullie,</hi> who as he could haue done it as well, and peraduenture better than <hi>Saluſt, Caeſar</hi> or <hi>Liui</hi> ſo will he alſo ſharpen our iudgement that way, that we ſhall be able not onelye to doe the lyke, but alſo as it may ſometimes happen peraduenture better. <hi>Pollio</hi> as <hi>Quintilian</hi> reporteth, ſpyed a certaine patiuinitie in
<pb facs="tcp:18511:41"/>
               <hi>Liuies</hi> ſtile, which he coulde not haue iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged nor conſidered, if he had not learned of the beſt authors, the true properties of the romaine, and of the patauine ſpéech. And he which hath his mouth well waſhed and ſeaſoned with <hi>Tullies</hi> waters: ſhall be able with the ſame to féele in <hi>Liuie,</hi> as <hi>Pollio</hi> did a kinde of ſtraunge ſpéeche, and a certayne peregrinitie, if I may ſo terme it. And hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto of that queſtion in which was aſked: what is moſt chieflye to be imitated, and what other beſides him. For <hi>Cicero</hi> muſt be followed firſt of all: and beſides him the beſt of euerie one in his kinde. It followeth, that we declare what thing we ſhoulde imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate: and what order is to be obſerued ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which part, although it be long, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to all the preceptes of eloquence: yet will we conclude it in a fewe poyntes. For all this deliberation beginneth of one heade, and that is immediatlye deuided into two braunches. For firſt of all, we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whervnto the matter or argument doth tende, which we haue taken in hande to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and expreſſe. Next this, we muſt ſée af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18511:41"/>what maner it ſhoulde be handled, and what wordes and ſentences are requiſite for the beautifying and ſetting forth of the ſame. And for this cauſe in the definition of imitation, did I comprehende and include the maner of handling, and the kinde of vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teraunce: And plaine it is, that if we meane to write a Dialogue, and to bring men in to commen togither, we ſhoulde not ſéeke in <hi>Tullies</hi> Orations for a patterne to followe, but rather in his Tuſculande or Academi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call queſtions, or in his other like diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. So if we haue an Oration, Como<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, Tragidie, or Satire to write: it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, whither we ought to looke, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſhoulde direct both our eyes and our minde. This practiſe therefore beginneth at the argument or matter, and then it goeth out, as I ſaide, into two braunches. The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument I haue often termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, other name it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The kinde of ſpéech or forme of vtterance, I call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and as for the maner of handling we may at our pleaſure eyther call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not as though there were not a kinde of
<pb facs="tcp:18511:42"/>handling alſo in the formes of vtterance (for euerie one is handled after a peculier ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) but we apply handling properly to the thinges which be apt and agréeable for the ſame. But concerning the Argument, wée muſt vſe a choyſe. Wherein we muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the councell of <hi>Horace</hi> who doth aduiſe vs.</p>
            <q>
               <l>To chooſe ſuch matter when wee write,</l>
               <l>as fit is for our ſtrength:</l>
               <l>And long to wey and payſe the ſame,</l>
               <l>vntill we know at length</l>
               <l>How much our ſhouldiours may ſustaine,</l>
               <l>and what they will not beare.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which ſtrength of ours is greatly increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wyth diligence, for theſe which are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to other in wit, and learning, ought by the example of good Orators, and of the beſt writers, to helpe themſelues with diligence. Wherby it commeth to paſſe, that ſtrength is to be meaſured by thrée things, that is, by wit, knowledge, &amp; by dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For he which is endued with ſharpneſſe of witte, and hath gotten learning to guide &amp; accompanie the ſame: If he adde diligence, and continuall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18511:42"/>exerciſe therevnto, it muſt néedes be a harde matter, that he ſhal not be able to ſet forth in writing, and polliſh with his pen. But we cannot fully declare this part of our conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation before the time of imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be known: And for bycauſe mention is made of habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, witte, and learning: we will brieflye ſpeake of this laſt poynt, that is to ſaye, at what time imitation ſhoulde be begoonne: which is not ſo much to be meaſured by age and yeares, as by ſtrength and habilitie.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as <hi>Ariſtotell</hi> did exclude yong boyes from his Ethickes: So I alſo remoue from this artificial practiſe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly children and boyes: but alſo thoſe men which know not the preceps of Rhetorick, neyther haue attained to anye vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of learning, nor haue not a ſinguler de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make their ſpéech &amp; ſtile like vnto that which is moſt praiſe worthie, and of the beſt ſorte. For as I thinke, this cauſed <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell</hi> to baniſh boyes and yong men from his doctrine: for that he ſawe in them neyther conſtant promptneſſe of will, nor morall iudgement. So we alſo vnto this practiſe &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18511:43"/>trade of imitating doe admitte him whoſe minde is inflamed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of eloquence and whoſe breſt is not barren and voide of ſome knowledge of learning. But as for the ignorant or ſluggiſhe ſorte, we commit them to the teachers of other Artes, which can better away with them, vntill ſuch time as they be further inſtructed and more inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged. Therfore, when the minde is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and in ſuch a readineſſe, as I haue ſayde, than is the fitteſt time to beginne this practiſe: Howbeit, I require not exquiſite learning for this matter, I am content with this your indifferent ſkill. Neuertheleſſe, there be thrée times appointed for this prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: one while we are learning of it, which is the firſt, another, when we haue learned it, and that is the middle time, and the thirde and laſt time is, when we perfitlye knowe and vnderſtande it. For ſo long we ought to learne this Arte, vntil we haue gotten it, and that wée be able to deuiſe and make ſomewhat, that may be publiſhed worthie the hearing of all men, and acceptable to the learned. But when we haue gotten and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18511:43"/>obtayned both the knowledge of this, and of many things beſides, euen as a player that hath béene well practiſed in playing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond part, may afterwarde well ynough be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to play the firſt parte, and to ſhewe himſelfe vpon the ſtage: So alſo your ſtile, after it ſhall be filed in this ſorte, ſhall not néede to feare the opinion of the multitude, nor to dread the iudgement of learned men. As for the third tyme, when we are growne to perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: although it be to be wiſhed, and though we ought to labor al we can, that we ſhould the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſéeme to néede no more examples: yet I doubt whether euer anye man ſhall attaine therevnto. For in ſo great varietie and excellencie of Philoſophers, Orators, Hiſtorians, &amp; Poets, there will be alwayes ſomewhat, which eyther we haue not read or not marked before: ſo that ſtill we haue ſome thing to encreaſe our knowledge. For it is a hard matter to reade and vnderſtande all things: and to remember all thinges, I think it can neuer happen to a mortall man.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, we muſt labour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede as farre as we can. For it is ſhamefull
<pb facs="tcp:18511:44"/>to ſtaye in a vertuous, commendable and a glorious race, when you maye runne fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſpecially ſéeing the laſt traueiles for the moſt part are more eaſie and pleaſant than the firſt. Howbeit, this is alſo true that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you cannot be comparable or ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to the moſt perfite: yet is it good and commendable to contend with them in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things: and to go beyonde them in ſome things, if we be able: and eyther to adde or take away, or chaunge ſomewhat in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions and enſamples of them, whom we doe imitate, and to attempt and labour to doe ſomewhat, which maye be better: and hath euermore bene graunted to all men in all times. For imitation ought to be frée, and not ſeruile or ſlauiſh. Neyther will we that an imitator doe alwayes followe the ſteps of another: but diuers times and as oft as he can, if he maye doe it decently, let him out runne him that went before. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, before a yong man hath ſome taſte in learning, &amp; before he haue ſome vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Rhetoricke and Logicke: I will not admit him into this ſchoole, but will leaue
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18511:44"/>him to the Grammarians, whoſe vulgares and preſcriptes he muſt yet follow, as lynes that be drawne by another man. But when he hath once obteyned theſe thinges: if he haue wit, and if there be in him a loue and an earneſt deſire to eloquence, as appeareth in you: than ſhall this ſchoole be open for him, and we will trie what this order and practiſe can worke in him. And in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this exerciſe, whomſoeuer we ſhall account the beſt writer in any tongue: him ſhall we reade with great diligence: and firſt, we ſhall conſider what he ſayth: next, in what order, &amp; with what kinde of vtterance, and by what Methode or maner of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Wherof the firſt pertaineth to inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but order is referred to collocation: and the kinde of vtteraunce belongeth to the forme of ſpeache. And as for the maner of handeling, which doth chieflye cauſe and make this forme: it conteyneth aſwell the ornaments and figures of ſpeach, as the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of ſentences and reaſons, as alſo the framing, knitting and numerouſneſſe both of members and whole Periodes, with the
<pb facs="tcp:18511:45"/>varietie of all thoſe things compared togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which being taught in Arte, are here ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and as a man would ſay, are drawne out, and ſet forth in their colours: All theſe thinges muſt be layde vp in ſtore, and noted in that volume wherof we haue ſpoken: that we may haue them in readineſſe as ofte as we ſhall néede: to the intent we may ſée in euerie matter that we take in hande, what ſteppes we ſhoulde followe, and where wée ſhould treade.</p>
            <p>Therefore this is the firſt tyme that wée haue to beſtowe this way: diligently in our example to obſerue and marke thoſe things that Arte hath taught vs before. Neyther ought we to ſtay, vntill we know all things, and vntill our volume be filled. But imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after the beginning, ſo ſoone as wée haue marked any thing, we muſt take Pen in hande, and frame ſomewhat that may be lyke the ſame. And in this place touching the Argument and matter, we muſt kéepe this rule that we beginne alwayes with the eaſieſt things, that we cloye not our ſelues, and make our labor more painefull with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18511:45"/>Wherefore if we will imitate E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles: we muſt at the beginning chooſe the ſhorteſt, and in Orations, long Epiſtles, &amp; Philoſophicall diſputations, we muſt imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate a ſhort péece, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> concluſion of a reaſon or a ſimilitude, or a compariſon, or a bréefe narration, or a common place, and a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſentence, or a contrarie. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that theſe things pertaine not ſo much to the matter and argument, as to the maner of handling the ſame: whereof wée will ſpeake euen anone. Howbeit, this rule well ſerueth for this place, that euerie thing be done in his kinde. For euen as he that woulde write an Hyſtorie, muſt followe an Hyſtorian: and he that penneth a Satire, woulde take example of <hi>Horace</hi> or <hi>Perſius,</hi> and a maker of Tragidies take <hi>Euripides,</hi> or <hi>Sophocles</hi> to be his patterne: ſo here alſo, foraſmuch as there is great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the courtly ſpéeche of Orators, and the talke of Philoſophers, and the familiar, and daily communication of men: as euery one of theſe, is in their owne proper kinde, ſuch muſt alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example be. But it is hard
<pb facs="tcp:18511:46"/>to iudge of what ſort and nature a thing is. and ought to be. Wherefore, I will from henceforth ſpeake as I haue begoone, of the maner of imitating: Wherein is firſt to be conſidered, what things be imitable: and againe, what thinges they are that we can not imitate. I call that imitable, that we may by following obteyne and expreſſe: of the Gréekes called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Whereby is vnderſtoode what is not imitable, which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now to begin ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or to take ſuch things in hande, as are not imitable, were méere follie. But of ſuch things there are two kindes: one is not imitable by nature: the other at certaine times. <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſayth that wit in inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vehemence and facilitie are not imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: and he ſayth true, for theſe thinges are borne with a man, and are proper to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans nature &amp; not to ours. Neither can they be gotten or taught by Arte: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they appeare in our enſample: theſe things therefore by nature pertaine not to imitation: although in imitation they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare and ſhewe: and through this ererciſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18511:46"/>our naturall powers alſo are ſtirred vp and inſtructed, and made more ſtrong: yet this kinde, bicauſe of nature it is not imitable, pertaineth nothing to this our purpoſe. For it dependeth of another mans wit and not of ours. But there are alſo certaine works of other men ſo framed, that they ſéeme to be ſet aboue our capacities: euen as <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar</hi> ſéemed in the iudgement of <hi>Horace.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Who Pindars verſe doth ſtudie to excell.</l>
               <l>Friend Iule, doth with Dedals waxed winges</l>
               <l>Aſsaye to flie to Pontus yſie Pole</l>
               <l>A name to giue.</l>
            </q>
            <p>He alſo rendreth the reaſon thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <l>From tipe of hill as riuers runne amaine,</l>
               <l>Which daily ſures on bankes aboue increaſe,</l>
               <l>So Pindars verſe as fast doth flowe</l>
               <l>In mouth profounde.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Horace</hi> ſuppoſeth that this grauitie and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Pindarus,</hi> if I may ſo terme it, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be imitated. But though therebe certain workes of great Artificers which at the firſt muſt not be dealt withall, bicauſe we cannot reache them: yet in time notwithſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:18511:47"/>they are made more eaſie. For it is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto a beginner to make a whole Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or worke: neyther woulde I councell him to doe it, though it were giuen him. For time wil bréede in him a greater habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and bring vnto him a greater facilitie: wherefore, let the firſt labour be beſtowed in the eaſieſt parts of workes, and in the leaſt porcion of the ſame: and then by little and little we maye procéede to greater and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and at the length to the whole worke, and finally: we maye not deſpaire, no not in the moſt perfite of all. For eyther we ſhall obteyne our deſire, or we ſhall get from thence ſome excellent furniture to finiſhe that which nature hath made vs able to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieue, as <hi>Horace</hi> writeth that he alſo did.</p>
            <q>
               <l>I as a morning Bee,</l>
               <l>a little wretch</l>
               <l>That ſeekes the woodes and Tiber bankes about,</l>
               <l>With labor great the pleaſant Time to ſucke,</l>
               <l>In maner doe my painefull crabbed verſe with labour ſing.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But this modeſtie in <hi>Horace</hi> is laudable,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18511:47"/>bicauſe he attributes the chiefe price to <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar:</hi> &amp; exhorteth <hi>Anthonie Iulius</hi> to a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er veyne, as though he ſhould leaue the little Rebeck, and playe on the great Violl. For neyther is there any thing more to be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of an Imitator than arrogancie: which is euer a companion of lightneſſe and follie. And yet did not <hi>Horace</hi> diſpaire: For in many things he is equall with <hi>Pindar:</hi> and diuers times he contendeth with him both wiſely and commendably. But bicauſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate imitation is ridiculous, he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of himſelfe modeſtlye: and warneth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wiſely, that they take nothing vppon them paſſing their habylities: ſpecially if they meane it ſhall come to light, and abide the iudgement of the learned. But at home we may aſſay and attempt what we liſt, and we maye ſtill ſtaye in them ſo long as we profite. But the beginning of this trade muſt be imployed vpon the eaſieſt and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarieſt thinges. I call that neceſſarye, whereof we haue vſe, not only at ſomtimes, but at all times. Such are thoſe thinges that I named before, among the which we ought
<pb facs="tcp:18511:48"/>to ſée what is worthie of imitation. For whatſoeuer is worthie of prayſe, that eyther plaintly appeareth, or is cloſely hidden. The one kinde wée call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, apparent or euident, vſing therein a mathematicall terme: the other we name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is as much as hidden, cloſe, or ſecret. I accompt apparant things: as wordes are, and the poliſhing of them, and the ioyning of them togither, as the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, placing and framing of thoſe things that be inuented. Hidden and ſecret poyntes are theſe. A ſignification of an amiable honeſtie in the Orator: ſometime a further meaning than is expreſſed in wordes: the leauing out of ſome wordes, reaſons, and ſentences that might haue bene put in: alſo beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and poliſhings omitted, which might haue bene vſed. Which are of ſo great weight that whoſoeuer paſſeth by them, and ſée them not, ſhall neuer worke any excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent feate. For as it appertaineth to vertue, not onely to chooſe thoſe thinges which are good and laudable, but alſo to ſhunne thoſe things that are euill: and as vertue it ſelfe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18511:48"/>ſometimes is vnderſtoode when it is not ſéene, ſo alſo it is the duetie of an Imitator not only to vewe that which is manifeſtlye ſhewed and plainly vttered, but alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is ſecret, and is not expreſſed. Therfore an Imitator hath néede of ſkilfull eyes: firſt for that theſe ſecrret poyntes are not eſpied till they be reuealed: then, bicauſe thoſe things alſo which are apparant, are oftentimes by the writers themſelues ſo conioyned and knittogither, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perceyued, but by a quicke ſighted workeman, and a ſkilfull maiſter. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beginning of this practiſe muſt haue the helpe of a teacher if he maye be gotten: to giue vs our matter and argument, to tell vs what is to be imitated, to teache vs, to correct vs, to ſhewe vs howe we maye hide and couer lyke thinges by vnlike vſing and handling the ſame. For he ought to be a hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his Arte, which would be a good Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator. To follow our example in euery point is very childiſh. For although it be artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to followe the picture of <hi>Venus</hi> drawne by <hi>Apelles,</hi> (which was called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:18511:49"/>for that ſhe ſéemed to riſe out of the ſea) or to paynt a Satyre or fieldiſhe Maumet in ſuch ſort as <hi>Protogenes</hi> did: and to vſe the ſame colours, lineaments, and ſhadowes, which they did, and to differ from them in no point at all: yet is it more excellent to expreſſe in <hi>Apollo</hi> or <hi>Achylles,</hi> the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame Arte which <hi>Apelles</hi> ſhewed in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeytinge the images of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> or <hi>Priamus,</hi> though therein you haue only fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the documents and draughtes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles.</hi> Therefore we muſt firſt endeuour that our doing may appeare vnlike the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne: Secondly, if it doe ſéeme like, yet let vs ſo vſe the matter, that it maye be thought we made it ſo of ſet purpoſe: which is the vſe ſometime of learned men. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, this muſt neuer be done but when it is commendable to contende with our pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne: and when that elegancie is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, though the matters be not of one ſort, but different, and not ſo like in kinde as in the maner of handling.</p>
            <p>There are many Orations of <hi>Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> and many of <hi>Ciceros:</hi> but yet in theſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18511:49"/>Orations of <hi>Cicero,</hi> yea, euen in his Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippickes, which ſhewe by the title after what patterne they were ſhaped: <hi>Tullie</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame kindes of ſpéeche and formes of vtteraunce that <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> dyd: yet doth of purpoſe endeuor to differ from him, although he followed <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. What difference is there betwéene the ſayings &amp; doings of <hi>Aeneas</hi> in <hi>Vergill,</hi> and the words of <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> in <hi>Homer.</hi> What is ſo like, as often times the forme of ſpeach in both theſe Poetes: and yet in this great likeneſſe, what great diuerſitie is there? what great varietie? that almoſt in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon talke we do not ſo properly ſay <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> in <hi>Homer</hi> as <hi>Aeneas</hi> in <hi>Vergill.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſometimes I like well that our I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation ſhoulde appéere and be perceiued: neither doe I miſlyke that beginning of <hi>Bembus: <hi>My Eather</hi> Bembus, <hi>deare fryende</hi> Tupoll:</hi> which he made to the exſample of <hi>Tullies</hi> beginning of his booke, called <hi>Brutus.</hi> For as <hi>Tullie</hi> hearing of <hi>Horten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> death, conceiued greater gréefe of mind, than any man woulde haue ſuppoſed: ſo
<pb facs="tcp:18511:50"/>his father <hi>Bembus,</hi> when tidings came to the Senate of <hi>Venice,</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines</hi> death, conceiued verily great gréefe, and ſorow, as <hi>Tullie</hi> doth: and as <hi>Tullies</hi> griefe increaſed in writing and vtteraunce, ſo doth <hi>Bembus</hi> his in lyke ſort. Now whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bembus</hi> for ſome purpoſe woulde haue it perceiued, that his writing was like to <hi>Tullies,</hi> or whether he thought it coulde not be ſpied: truely for my part, in ſteade of the gréefe that he and his father conceiued, in reading of this, I reaped great pleaſure, and while I conſidered it, I remembred this practiſe, which I nowe ſpeake of. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe an Imitator muſt hide all ſimilitude and likeneſſe: which is neuer prayſed but when it is comparable with the patterne, and yet cannot be perceiued by what means and in what places, and examples it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe. But this meanes of hyding ſtandeth in thrée things: In addition, abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, alteration, and chaunging: wherein is contained, coniunction, figuration, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and tranſformation, both of wordes and ſentences, of members, and periodes.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18511:50"/>Nowe as for addition, and ablation, what they be, it may be eaſily vnderſtood by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. The Gréekes call the one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the other <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and oftentimes a word or a littell péece, or a member, and the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence contained therein being eyther added, or taken away, cauſeth a new forme or y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of ſpeach. As for example, <hi>Tullie</hi> ſayth thus: <hi>I conceiued greater griefe of mind than any man would haue ſuppoſed.</hi> But <hi>Bembus</hi> thus: <hi>He conceyued verily great griefe and ſorowe.</hi> But theſe two poynts, I meane addition and ablation, are ſeldome vſed without the other, which if wée want our imitation, is but childiſhe. I call alteration <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one part of the which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which conſiſteth in the diuers placing of wordes and things, and is wrought by putting of wordes, members, ſentences, and other things neceſſarie either before, or after, or in the middeſt.</p>
            <p>Figuration, is of the Gréekes termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is chiefly in genders, numbers, and caſes: for the varietie of theſe bringeth delight, &amp; taketh away ſaſiety. But
<pb facs="tcp:18511:51"/>as in making, ſo alſo in hiding, and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging we ought to doe that which is deſent, and to traine euerie thing as beſt beſéemeth. Communication is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and it is when one worde, or thing ſerueth in the ſteade or place of an other: which in wordes is named <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in things it is called a diuers argumentation, when diuers ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and reaſons pertaine to one purpoſe, euen as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, concauſes or ioyned cauſes, be in things done, or brought to effect, and in concluſions are the collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſilogiſmes of manye reaſons. I name tranſformation, that which the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians terme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which containeth all the figures of Rhetoricke: for both the Metaphores and tropes of wordes, and alſo the ornamentes and beautifications of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences are oftentimes of lyke force, and therefore it is lawfull to chaunge the one with the other, neyther is there anye thing wherin an Imitator may more glorie, than in turquifing, and tranſlating of things and wordes, and the cowpling and knitting of the ſame: in the which is required not onely
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18511:51"/>diuerſitie, but alſo varietie: therefore tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuring hath adioyned vnto it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we may terme variation, bycauſe it taketh away ſaſietie, and is commonly the chiefe cauſer of all pleaſure and delight. And this difference is betwéene <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that the laſt maketh a diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of workes: the other varietie, in onelye one worke: neyther is there any thing more pleaſaunt and exceptable to the eare, than to heare one thing often expreſſed in other wordes, and to ſee euerie where diuerſitie of ornamentes, and varietie of Periods, wyth chaunge of numbers in the clauſes of the ſame by diſtaunt places. And theſe are the things which hide Arte &amp; ſimilitude, which although they ſéeme but trifles: yet are they the onely dooers of that, which the eares of the learned deſire to heare, neyther is it knowne what force is in them vntill wée haue tryed it by vſe and practiſe.</p>
            <p>But this muſt alwayes be remembred, that no hiding is worthie prayſe, which doth not beſtowe in the place of that which wée imitate, a thing eyther as good or better:
<pb facs="tcp:18511:52"/>or if it ſéeme baſer, yet it may appeare to be done not without ſome purpoſe and reaſon. That circumſcription of <hi>Vergil. Arma vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque cano. &amp;c.</hi> That is, <hi>of armes, and of a Captaynecke I doe indite. &amp;c.</hi> Who ſéeth not that it is framed to the ſimilitude of <hi>Homers</hi> beginning: Yet is there this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwéene them, that <hi>Homer</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Achilles</hi> by his proper name, &amp; brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye requieſteth the muſe to recite his wrath, and what miſchiefe it ſtirred amonge the Grecians. <hi>Vergill</hi> doth not name his <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas,</hi> but ſheweth his purpoſe at large in more wordes: ſo that though we will not graunt <hi>Vergill</hi> to be ſuperior: yet of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie muſt we confeſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his is a goodly and beautifull beginning, and equal to <hi>Homers,</hi> if the Gréekes wil not be diſpleaſed with vs for ſo ſaying. But not withſtanding it is honeſt ſome tymes to yéelde and giue place, when the thing we purpoſe doth ſo require. And to continue in the ſame example which I vſed before: who gaine ſaith but this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentence is more ful and numerous: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued greater griefe of minde than anye
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18511:52"/>man woulde haue ſuppoſed, yet is the other alſo modeſt and fit for the preſent matter. <hi>He conceiued verily great griefe &amp; ſorow.</hi> But to returne to the matter: in ſteade of that which we imitate, we muſt alwayes place eyther a better thing or as good, or ſuch as is inferior for ſome ſpeciall cauſe: and we muſt thinke that thoſe thrée poyntes are then truely obſerued, when they doe not onely hide our ſteppes, but alſo doe garniſh, and ſet forth the matter: for whatſoeuer is artificiall, that alſo ought to be fine &amp; trym. And thoſe thrée things which I talked of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, be of greater force, and do more beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the matter, than vnſkilfull perſons would imagine. For figuration is one of the ſmalleſt things: but is it not pleaſaunt in that compariſon of <hi>Vergill.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>O happie art thou Tityrus,</l>
               <l>that vnder Beechen tree,</l>
               <l>Thy ſong in Pipe of ſlender Ote,</l>
               <l>doste ſounde with voyce ſo free.</l>
               <l>But we alas our Countrie costes,</l>
               <l>and pleaſant fieldes forſake:</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:18511:53"/>
               <l>We flie our natiue ſoyle,</l>
               <l>but thou in ſhade thy eaſe doste take,</l>
               <l>And makste the woodes for to reſounde</l>
               <l>alowde faire Amarill.</l>
            </q>
            <p>What can be leſſe then: thou <hi>Tityrus, <hi>and wee are expulſed,</hi>
               </hi> yet this chaunge of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers hath a marueylous grace: and for that cauſe, as the order is of this kinde of verſe: <hi>Tityrus</hi> doth alſo imitate the ſame elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, the which he doth without anye arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, or enuious emulation, bicauſe the ſhepeherde <hi>Melibeus</hi> was his friende.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O Melibey our God to vs</l>
               <l>this quiet ſtate did will,</l>
               <l>For he, for aye ſhall be my God,</l>
               <l>vpon his Altar ſtone:</l>
               <l>Oft ſhall the tender Lambe bee ſlaine,</l>
               <l>from ſheepefoldes of our owne.</l>
            </q>
            <p>You ſée howe in like ſort he hath chaunged the number, for in the one place he ſayth: our God to vs: and in the other: for he for aye ſhall be my God. As therfore this kinde is elegant, when we write without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample after our owne deuiſe: ſo alſo when we write with an example and patterne
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18511:53"/>to followe, it is both elegant and couereth that which we ſéeke after and woulde not haue knowne. I néede not diſcourſe of all thoſe points which I propounded before: for you haue partlye hearde them of me, and partly they are vnderſtoode by themſelues, and at this time are not to be throughly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled. Howbeit, I will yet put one example more, and that ſhall be of tranſformation. There is an excellent and proper conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſentences in <hi>Theocritus,</hi> which the Gréekes doe call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we may name it a counterchaunge.</p>
            <q>
               <l>If he ſhall chooſe the horned Scire,</l>
               <l>The female Goate ſhall be thine hire.</l>
               <l>But if he doe the female take,</l>
               <l>Thou with a Kidde ſhalt merie make,</l>
               <l>Kiddes fleſh is good and ſweete perdee,</l>
               <l>Vntill at Paile they milked bee.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In ſteade of this conuerſion <hi>Vergill</hi> vſed a circle, whereof I ſpake before: and for theſe wordes which <hi>Theocritus</hi> repeateth, <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil</hi> reherſeth other: and who can denie but the one doth follow the example of the other. But ſome will ſay, he vſeth not the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing
<pb facs="tcp:18511:54"/>of his ſentence, nor the ſame wordes that <hi>Theocritus</hi> doth. I graunt it, and that did he to the intent that vnſkilfull perſons ſhould not perceyue his ſteppes. But why did he not ſo in that which followeth: <hi>Non equidem inuideo:</hi> that is, I enuie not thy happie ſtate, ſéeing <hi>Theocritus</hi> alſo writeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: forſooth bicauſe he woulde haue it knowne whome he imitateth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he would not haue it ſpyed, how and after what ſort he doth it. But peraduenture ſome man will denie that this was done by imitation, ſéeing the thinges be not all one in both the writers. I aunſwere that imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not in things that be all one, but in things that be like, and that which is like, muſt be, not the ſame, but another thing, and yet nere vnto it, which neareneſſe is meaſured by the ende and forme of the ſpeache: as in theſe verſes the ende of a ſhepeherdes ſong is ſwéeteneſſe, and for that cauſe <hi>Thyrſis</hi> in <hi>Theocritus</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſonge of the ſhepeherde <hi>Aepolus</hi> ſayth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, this whuz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing winde doth ſwéetely blowe: and by and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18511:54"/>by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe is. <hi>And thou thy Pipe doste ſweetlye ſounde:</hi> and ſo for pleaſure and delight as <hi>Theocritus</hi> repeateth in this worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and vſeth that conuerſion we ſpeake off: ſo likewiſe <hi>Vergill</hi> doth iterate, <hi>Nos patriae fines,</hi> and <hi>Nos patriam fugimus,</hi> and in ſteade of the conuerſion, he concludeth his ſentence, as a man woulde ſaye in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine circle and compaſſe. Euery man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the beginning of <hi>Homer</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>O Muſe recite <hi>Achylles</hi> wrath. &amp;c.</hi> Which vndoubtedly is a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſitte for <hi>Homer,</hi> both graue and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and méete for the purpoſe he had in hande. Neuertheleſſe <hi>Vergils</hi> beginning <hi>Arma virumque cano. &amp;c. <hi>Of warres and Armes I doe endite, and of that Captayne bolde &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> hath as manye and as great gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in it, as <hi>Homers</hi> hath: and certainly it is altogither Heroicall, and though it much differ from <hi>Homers,</hi> yet hath it a certayne artificiall likeneſſe to the ſame conſiſting in the grauitie and beautification, which is couered by thoſe meanes whereof I ſpake
<pb facs="tcp:18511:55"/>before. For as <hi>Homer</hi> ſheweth the wrath and furie of <hi>Achylles,</hi> ſo <hi>Vergill</hi> painteth out <hi>Aeneas</hi> with more wordes and ſpeciall tokens: ſo that in the perſons there is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie, and in the handling there is a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which ought to be applied to the ende, which is grauitie. And for this cauſe hath he briefly comprehended manye and great matters. Now touching <hi>Homers</hi> ſwéete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of letters and voyces, and the ſounde of Poeticall woordes, which are proper to the Gréeke tongue: <hi>Vergil</hi> hath fullye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed that grace with a moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full figuration. <hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Arma virumquè:</hi> of armes &amp; of that Captaine bold: <hi>Italiam Lauinaquè littora,</hi> to <hi>Itaile</hi> lande and <hi>Lauine</hi> ſhores: <hi>Terris iactatus &amp; alto:</hi> by ſeas and eke by lande ytoſte: both numbers ſingular and plurall are thriſe knit togither: and in that verſe <hi>Vi ſuperam ſaeue memorem Iuno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ob iram:</hi> through force of Gods, and for the mindefull wrath of <hi>Iuno</hi> fell:</hi> not only numbers are ioyned, but alſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, combining and apt knitting of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is featly chaunged: likewiſe that which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18511:55"/>followeth. <hi>Genus vnde Latinum, Albani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>què patres, atquè altae maenia Romae:</hi> from whence the line of Latine bloud and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane</hi> fathers came, and loftie walles of <hi>Rome</hi> doe riſe: what diſtinction of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, numbers, vowels or voyces is there: and laſtly, <hi>Muſa mihi cauſas memora. &amp;c.</hi> O Muſe recite to mée the cauſes of this griefe: doth both differ from the inuocation of <hi>Homer</hi> by order and placing: and in greatneſſe is aunſwerable to <hi>Homers</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: and beſide theſe excellent poyntes he doth not only aſke a queſtion, but alſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth: woondereth &amp; crieth out. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the imitation of this like matter is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, by placing, chaunging, adding, and by varying: for <hi>Vergil</hi> hath ſeperated the propoſition from that inuocation, and hath chaunged the perſons and matters, and hath recited more plentie of things which is proper to addition: and by the varietie of wordes, genders, caſes, and numbers, all thinges are ſounding, which is méete for grauitie: and yet is this ſo done, as neyther the elegancie doth marre the grauitie, nor
<pb facs="tcp:18511:56"/>the grauitie is a hinderaunce vnto the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie. Wherefore, when we will handle diuers matters after a like maner, we muſt doe it couertlye, which is wrought by that meanes that I haue declared. Nowe after that we haue made choyſe both of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor whome we minde to imitate, and of the matter that we purpoſe to expreſſe: than the firſt conſideration ought to be of the kinde of vtterance, to the ende and forme whereof we muſt applie both our matter and wordes, and the placing and varietie of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But here it is neceſſarie and néedefull to haue a maiſter and teacher, and without Arte the ſecret Image of an Imitator, is not perceiued: and this order requireth great vſe and practiſe, and few there be that attaine vnto it. <hi>Saluſt</hi> is a noble Hiſtorian, and <hi>Quintilians</hi> teſtimonie of his breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is well knowne. But howe manye be there, that vnderſtande how it commeth to paſſe, and wherein it conſiſteth. <hi>Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeus</hi> writeth, that the compoſition of wordes in <hi>Thucidides</hi> is goodly and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18511:56"/>but nothing ſwéete or pleaſaunt, and contrariwiſe in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> it is pleaſaunt, but not goodly: But <hi>Herodotus</hi> compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as he ſaith is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> both plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt and goodly: ſurely it pertaineth to a ſharpe and well practiſed iudgement, and as a man woulde ſaye, to a pierſing eye to ſée wherein comlineſſe and delectation conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and howe goodlineſſe differeth from ſwéetneſſe and pleaſantneſſe: not as though there were but ſmall difference betwéene vertue and pleaſure: but for that, that in ſpéeche, eligancie and ſwauitie are not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſeuered, therefore both Arte is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and a teacher requiſite, and there née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth practiſe and experience beſide. It is commonly ſayde that <hi>Vergils</hi> Georgickes are perfite and that his <hi>Aeneidos</hi> are not ſo throughly filed. But I woulde méete with ſuch a fellow, an interpretor of Poetes, that coulde ſhew me this, and declare it vnto me where néede were. But of this matter at ſome other time: and nowe to our purpoſe, touching the forme of vtteraunce: whereof we muſt haue the Image before our eyes,
<pb facs="tcp:18511:57"/>whilſt we are working, and framing our matterwherevnto we muſt apply our ſtile, as it were our hande, with fit and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent wordes, and beautifications, which are in ſteade of colours, ſhadoings, and lightes, I call conueniencie, or fitneſſe, that which the Latines name <hi>decorum,</hi> and in oure engliſhe tongue ſéemelineſſe, which in all things, and ſpeciallye in imitation is moſt neceſſarie. Wherein two thinges muſt chiefly be obſerued, that is to wéete, aptneſſe and meaſure: aptneſſe is a continual agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thinges and wordes, meaſure is, when in ſuch things as doe agrée, there is neyther to much nor to little: as in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>Homers</hi> Iliades there wanteth nothing, and in the preamble of <hi>Vergils Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neidos</hi> there is nothing to much, notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it be larger and of greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe than <hi>Homers</hi> is, aptneſſe is conſidered in mouing, or ſtirring vp, in maners, and in nature: nature I attribute to ſuch things as pertaine not to men: as Earbes, Trées, Precious ſtones, Orchardes, Lands, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and ſuch lyke: which things are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18511:57"/>and expreſſed by a certaine and proper kinde of ſpéech fitte for the ſame. And moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings pertaine to Poetes and Orators, when they expreſſe the maners and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as wel of themſelues, as of other men: and when they ſtirre vp the mindes of the hearers or readers to wrath, hatred, loue, and to mercie: and hereof comes theſe kindes of elocution or vtteraunce, whereof <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaketh in his thirde booke of Rhetoricke, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is to ſay in engliſh, a patheticall or ſtirring kinde of vtteraunce, and a morall kinde: and the thirde, when the ſpéech is proportionable to the nature of things. Now what maner of vtterance theſe be, and ought to be, the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who is a paſſing maiſter and teacher of Arte, hath plainely ſhewed. Here haue I alſo to ſpeake of ſéemelineſſe, which I called <hi>decorum:</hi> that we doe not onely reſemble a bare image of this forme as it were the outward ſkinne, but alſo that the bloud, veines, ſinowes, and the verye brawnes, or force of the muſcules may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>péere
<pb facs="tcp:18511:58"/>forth and be ſéene. Wherfore we muſt labor and trauaile, that our ſpéeche may be beautifull, wiſe, and ſounde: of the which thrée, beautie, appertaines to elegancie, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to the things themſelues, and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to nature and comlineſſe: that the forme it ſelfe maye be naturall, agréeable, and ſéemely: neyther is it to be doubted but the picture of <hi>Venus,</hi> which <hi>Apelles</hi> pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as riſing out of the Sea, appeared to be ſprinkled with ſome forme of the Sea, but yet in ſuch ſorte, as the ſame did make the forme and beautie of the Goddeſſe more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable and louely. Wherefore as <hi>Apelles</hi> left ſome parte of that picture rude and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimmed: ſo likewiſe ought a writer, and Imitator to doe, and to conſider not howe far a thing may be beautified and ſet forth: but howe much poliſhing is méete therfore, which being not conſidered, the ſpéeche muſt néedes be both ſwelling and puffed vp, and alſo vnapt and fooliſh. Therefore they giue good aduice, which will vs to follow <hi>Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi> who often changeth <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> into ſundry formes, and ſometimes maketh
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18511:58"/>him a wrinkled, little, yll fauored fellowe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is to ſaye, <hi>lyke to a ſimple begging wretch, or like a withered Carle:</hi> ſometimes alſo touchinge him with hir Verge or Maſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Shee makes him fatte and groſse of fleſhe, and large of lymme to ſeeme. <hi>Et</hi>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>And on his heade the curled lockes, with grace ſhee makes to fall, much lyke a Purple Syacinth which wee doe Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes call:</hi> euen thus muſt alſo an Orator doe, that he come not alwayes forth in a Silken and precious garment: but ofte times alſo in a worne cote, and common at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre, and ſuch as ſerueth for euerie daye. Nowe after we haue well conſidered what is ſéemelye and comely: we muſt gather things togither and ſet them in order, and get ſtore of wordes, and followe theſe waies and rules that I haue ſhewed: that nothing be done or placed without a cauſe: and yet after ſuch maner, that the common ſorte may not perceiue it. For as it is to be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb facs="tcp:18511:59"/>that our ſpéeche maye pleaſe all men, and as we ought ſpeciallye to indeuor to obtayne the ſame: ſo alſo we muſt take great héede, that Arte, and Imitation, and the ſimilitude and lykeneſſe be not eſpied.</p>
            <p>And thus much hitherto touching the ſtyle and imitation: wherein I thought it not beſt to proſecute all that might be ſaid: as how we ſhoulde tranſlate out of Gréeke into Latine, and after what maner we ſhould reſolue Poetes verſes into proſe, ſo that it might appeare to be no Poeme: alſo how we ſhoulde comment and deuiſe: and how we ſhould beginne and finiſhe a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: all the which things may then ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well be taken in hande, when we haue alreadie had good practiſe of thoſe thinges whereof I haue ſpoken: wherfore we will ſpeake hereof at another ſeaſon, and for this preſent time, let that which I haue ſayde, ſuffice for your ſtudies: ſpecially bicauſe you haue me yet preſent with you: Let vs beginne therefore this courſe againe, and come afreſh to that great reading and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting whereof we ſpake. Reading is of two
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18511:59"/>ſorts, the one for enſample to imitate, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to get knowledge and vnderſtanding: of the which two, the one requireth a pawſe or ſtaye: that thoſe thinges which are hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the example, may be fetched forth and ſéene, the other is to runne ouer the matter, and to marke and remember manye and ſundrie thinges. Therefore it muſt be vſed and applyed as I ſayd in the beginning, and verily there is no doubt but we maye both reade ouer all <hi>Tullie,</hi> and vnderſtand him within thrée yeares, taking onelye the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wres in the forenoone: Moreouer, we may note much in him for imitation: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer remayneth ſhall ſerue for the yeares following. Now for other Authors, who can denie but we maye learne much euen of thoſe that I named before, as Orators, Hyſtorians, Philoſophers, and Poetes, ſo that theſe thrée peres ſpace may both make our ſpeach beautifull, and furniſh vs with wiſedome and knowledge of diuers things. Both which, if you ſhall atchieue, you may be patternes and examples to men of your ſtate and degrée. And ſurely next to warre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:18511:60"/>proweſſe which conſiſteth as well in the experience of ſuch affaires as in valiant and hautie courage: what doth more become a noble man, or more agree with auncient linage, than honeſt maners, a learned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, a wiſe tongue, and the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of all antiquitie, and the knowledge of all kinds of gouernements and common welthes. Were not <hi>Contarenus Bembus</hi> and <hi>Sadolecus</hi> in the number of Cardinals as Lampes and lights. In the Emperours Court, howe great an ornament was the Biſhop of <hi>Atrebat.</hi> Is not Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce honored by reaſon of Cardinall <hi>Bellaius:</hi> and at this preſent bicauſe of Cardinall <hi>Guiſe</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Maſcon. Iulius Pflug</hi> mine hoſte and patrone, is he not the beautie of Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie? What a name and commendation got <hi>Iames Sturmius</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Corlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice</hi> for learninges ſake. And though all theſe were Gentlemen, and of great cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, yet was their Gentrie, being honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it ſelfe, the more renowmed bicauſe of learning. If our countrie of Germanie, and the families of great men were gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18511:60"/>by ſuche perſonages we ſhoulde not néede to feare any daungerous chaunge of things, or any barbarous cuſtomes, or any deformitie of the Church and religion. I therefore writing theſe thinges vnto you, doe encourage all Gentlemen to theſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which if they greatlye beſéeme all ſtates of men, ſurelye they doe chiefly become Gentlemen, who for that they are aboue other in honor and glorie, ought the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to excell other in ſingular ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
